<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE xsl:stylesheet [<!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;"> <!ENTITY degree "&#176;">]>

<!-- Classes          
		A  - Corrosive
		HA - Highly Corrosive
 		C  - Carcinogenic 
 		E  - Explosive
 		HF - Highly Flammable
 		HT - Highly Toxic
 		MT - Mildly Toxic
 		MI - Mild Irritant
 		I  - irritant
 		O  - Oxidizer
 		T  - Toxic
 		SC - Silicosis / Cancer 		

<element>
	<an></an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n"></name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name></name>
			<formula></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></fcas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<classes>
				<class></class>
			</classes>		
			<notes>
				<ptxt></ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

Paul Alan Freshney 2008 [4344]

 -->

<compoundlist>

<element media="y" index="001" type="3">
	<an>1</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Hydrogen</name>
	<header>
		<ptxt>While H<sub>2</sub> is not very reactive under standard conditions, it does form compounds with most elements. <b>Millions</b> of hydrocarbons are known.</ptxt>
		<ptxt>Hydrogen can form compounds with elements that are more electronegative, such as <glink ref="halogens">halogens</glink> (e.g., <elink ref="9">F</elink>, <elink ref="17">Cl</elink>, <elink ref="35">Br</elink>, <elink ref="53">I</elink>) and chalcogens (<elink ref="8">O</elink>, <elink ref="16">S</elink>, <elink ref="34">Se</elink>); in these compounds <elink ref="1">hydrogen</elink> takes on a partial positive charge. When bonded to <elink ref="9">fluorine</elink>, <elink ref="8">oxygen</elink>, or <elink ref="7">nitrogen</elink>, <elink ref="1">hydrogen</elink> can participate in a form of strong noncovalent bonding called hydrogen bonding, which is critical to the stability of many biological molecules. Hydrogen also forms compounds with less electronegative elements, such as the metals and metalloids, in which it takes on a partial negative charge. These compounds are often known as hydrides.</ptxt>
	</header>
</element>

<element media="y" index="002" type="7">
	<an>2</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Helium</name>
	<header>
		<ptxt>Helium is chemically unreactive under all normal conditions due to its valence of zero. Because of this extreme conditions are needed to create the small handful of helium compounds, which are all unstable at standard temperature and pressure.</ptxt>
		<ptxt>No useful (with exception to those produced for scientific research) or commercial helium compounds exist.</ptxt>
	</header>
</element>

<element media="y" index="003" type="1">
	<an>3</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Lithium</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Lithium bromide</name>
			<formula>LiBr</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>7550-35-8</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp>825 K</mp>
			<bp>1538 K</bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>An extremely <glink ref="hygroscopic">hygroscopic</glink> and often used as a <glink ref="desiccant">dessicant</glink>. Along with lithium chloride (LiCl), it is frequently used in air conditioning and industrial drying systems.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Lithium carbonate</name>
			<formula>Li<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>554-13-2</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp>996 K</mp>
			<bp>1583 K</bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>A chemical compound that is used as a mood stabilizer in psychiatric treatment of manic states and bipolar disorder.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Lithium citrate</name>
			<formula>Li<sub>3</sub>C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>5</sub>O<sub>7</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>919-16-4</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp>? K</mp>
			<bp>? K</bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>A chemical compound that is used as a mood stabilizer in psychiatric treatment of manic states and bipolar disorder.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Lithium fluoride</name>
			<formula>LiF</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>7789-24-4</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp>1121 K</mp>
			<bp>1949 K</bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is a white, inorganic, crystalline, ionic, solid salt (under standard conditions). It transmits ultraviolet radiation more efficiently than any other substance. Uses include specialized UV optics and thermoluminescent dosimeters.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Lithium hydride</name>
			<formula>LiH</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp>962 K</mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It has numerous uses, as a <glink ref="desiccant">desiccant</glink>, among them as a precursor in chemical synthesis (in particular for lithium <elink ref="13">aluminium</elink> hydride), in <elink ref="1">hydrogen</elink> generators, as both a coolant and shielding in nuclear reactors, and in the manufacture of ceramics.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>One of its most infamous usages is as the fusion fuel in thermonuclear weapons, in the deuteride form; when this is irradiated with <glink ref="neutron">neutrons</glink>, lithium forms <elink ref="1">tritium</elink> (along with more <glink ref="neutron">neutrons</glink>, creating a chain reaction), which is a key ingredient in the thermonuclear reactions which power these devices.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Lithium hydroxide</name>
			<formula>LiOH</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>1310-65-2</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp>723 K</mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is made by mixing lithium and water. A reaction so violent, and so much heat is given off, that the <elink ref="1">hydrogen</elink> produced burns with a bright purple flame. For this reason, lithium batteries must be kept away from water.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Lithium hydroxide is used in breathing gas purification systems for spacecraft, submarines, and rebreathers to remove carbon dioxide (CO<sub>2</sub>) from exhaled gas by producing lithium carbonate (Li<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub>).</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Lithium iodide</name>
			<formula>LiI</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>10377-51-2</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Lithium <elink ref="53">iodide</elink> is used as an electrolyte for high temperature batteries. It is also used for long life batteries as required, for example, by cardiac pacemakers. The solid is used as a phosphor for <glink ref="neutron">neutron</glink> detection.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Lithium nitrate</name>
			<formula>LiNO<sub>3</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>10377-51-2</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp>528 K</mp>
			<bp>873 K</bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>An oxidizing agent used in the manufacture of fireworks and flares. It is <glink ref="deliquescent">deliquescent</glink>.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Lithium perchlorate</name>
			<formula>LiClO<sub>4</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>7791-03-9</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp>590 K</mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<classes>
				<class>I</class>
				<class>O</class>
			</classes>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Lithium perchlorate is used as a fuel and <elink ref="8">oxygen</elink> source in some chemical <elink ref="8">oxygen</elink> generators. As it has both the highest weight to <elink ref="8">oxygen</elink> and volume to <elink ref="8">oxygen</elink> ratio of all perchlorates, it is especially advantageous in aerospace applications.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>It is also used extensively as an electrolyte in lithium batteries.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Lithium peroxide</name>
			<formula>Li<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>12031-80-0</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp>468 K</mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is used in air purifiers such as those used in submarines to absorb carbon dioxide and release <elink ref="8">oxygen</elink>.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Lithium sulfate</name>
			<formula>Li<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>10377-48-7</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp>1126 K</mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is used to treat bipolar disorder.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Lithium tantalate</name>
			<formula>LiTaO<sub>3</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>12031-66-2</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp>1923 K</mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>A crystalline solid which possesses unique optical, piezoelectric and pyroelectric properties which make it valuable for infrared motion detectors, terahertz generation and detection, surface acoustic wave applications, cell phones and possibly pyroelectric nuclear fusion.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="004" type="4">
	<an>4</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Beryllium</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Beryllium oxide</name>
			<formula>BeO</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>1304-56-9</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp>2803 K</mp>
			<bp>4173 K</bp>
			<classes>
				<class>C</class>
			</classes>		
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Beryllium oxide is used in many high-performance semiconductor parts for applications such as radio equipment because it has good thermal conductivity while also being a good electrical insulator. It is also used as a structural ceramic for high-performance vacuum tubes, magnetrons, and gas lasers.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="005" type="0">
	<an>5</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="y">Boron</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Borax</name>
			<formula>Na<sub>2</sub>B<sub>4</sub>O<sub>7</sub> - 10H<sub>2</sub>O</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>1303-96-4</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is a soft white many-sided crystal that dissolves easily in water.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>is widely used in detergents, water softeners, soaps, disinfectants, and pesticides. Its use in detergents is due to its ability to bind to and solvate dirt particles in addition to producing peroxides which have a bleaching effect. One of its most widely advertised uses was as a hand-cleaner for industrial workers. It is used in making enamel glazes, glass and strengthening pottery and ceramics. It is also easily converted to boric <glink ref="acid">acid</glink> or borate, which have many applications. It is also used to make buffer solutions that are used in chemical analysis.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Large amounts of borax pentahydrate (Na<sub>2</sub>B<sub>4</sub>O<sub>7</sub> - 5H<sub>2</sub>O) are used for manufacturing insulating fibreglass and cellulose insulation as a fire retardant and anti-fungal compound. Large amounts are also used in production of <elink ref="11">sodium</elink> perborate monohydrate for use in detergents.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Boric Acid</name>
			<formula>H<sub>3</sub>BO<sub>3</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>10043-35-3</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>A mild <glink ref="acid">acid</glink> often used as an antiseptic, insecticide, flame retardant, in nuclear power plants to control the fission rate of <elink ref="92">uranium</elink>, and as a precursor of other chemical compounds. It exists in the form of colourless crystals or a white powder and dissolves in water.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Sodium borohydride</name>
			<formula>NaBH<sub>4</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>16940-66-2</cas>
			<density>1.0740</density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>A selective specialty reducing agent used in the manufacture of pharmaceuticals and other fine chemicals. It is a white solid, usually encountered as a powder or confectioned into pills.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>It is also being used in experimental fuel cell systems as a means of storing <elink ref="1">hydrogen</elink>. As a fuel it is less flammable and less volatile than gasoline but more corrosive. It is relatively environmentally friendly because it will quickly degrade into inert salts when released into the environment.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Rhenium diboride</name>
			<formula>ReB<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>A synthetic superhard material of hardness comparable to diamond. The production method of this material does not involve high pressures as with other hard synthetic materials, such as cubic boron nitride, which makes production cheap. The compound is formed from a mixture of rhenium, noted for its resistance to high pressure, and <elink ref="5">boron</elink>, which forms short, strong covalent bonds with rhenium. The resulting material is hard enough to scratch diamond.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>		
		<compound>
			<name>Sodium perborate</name>
			<formula>NaBO<sub>3</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It serves as a source of active <elink ref="8">oxygen</elink> in many detergents, laundry detergents, cleaning products, and laundry bleaches. It is also present in some tooth bleaching formulas. It has antiseptic properties and can act as a disinfectant.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>It is a less aggressive bleach than <elink ref="11">sodium</elink> hypochlorite, causing less degradation to dyes and textiles.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="006" type="3">
	<an>6</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="y">Carbon</name>
	<header>
		<ptxt>The abundance of carbon in the universe, along with the unusual polymer-forming ability of carbon-based compounds at the common temperatures encountered on Earth, make this element the basis of the chemistry of all known life.</ptxt>
		<ptxt>Carbon is the fourth most abundant chemical element in the universe by mass, after <elink ref="1">hydrogen</elink>, <elink ref="2">helium</elink>, and <elink ref="8">oxygen</elink>.</ptxt>
		<ptxt>Carbon is abundant in the sun, stars, comets, and in the atmospheres of most planets. Some meteorites contain microscopic diamonds that were formed when the solar system was still a protoplanetary disk. In combination with other elements, carbon is found in the earth's atmosphere (around 810 gigatonnes) and dissolved in all water bodies (around 36000 gigatonnes). Around 1900 gigatonnes are present in the biosphere. Hydrocarbons (such as coal, petroleum, and natural gas) contain carbon as well--coal "reserves" (not "resources") amount to around 1000 gigatonnes, and oil reserves around 150 gigatonnes. With smaller amounts of calcium, magnesium, and iron, carbon is a major component of very large masses carbonate rock (limestone, dolomite, marble etc.).</ptxt>
	</header>
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Carbon Dioxide</name>
			<formula>CO<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>124-38-9</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp>216 K (pressurized)</mp>
			<bp>195 K (sublimes)</bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Carbon dioxide is a colourless gas which, when inhaled at high concentrations (a dangerous activity because of the associated asphyxiation risk), produces a sour taste in the mouth and a stinging sensation in the nose and throat.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>This is a minor component of the Earth's atmosphere, produced and used by living things, and a common volatile elsewhere.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Carbon Monoxide</name>
			<formula>CO</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>630-08-0</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp>68 K</mp>
			<bp>81 K</bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Carbon monoxide, though thought of as a pollutant today, has always been present in the atmosphere, chiefly as a product of volcanic activity. It occurs dissolved in molten volcanic rock at high pressures in the earth's mantle. Carbon monoxide contents of volcanic gases vary from less than 0.01% to as much as 2% depending on the volcano.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Carbon monoxide is a significantly toxic gas with poisoning being the most common type of fatal poisoning in many countries. Symptoms of mild poisoning include headaches and flu-like effects; larger exposures can lead to significant toxicity of the central nervous system and heart.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>		
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="007" type="3">
	<an>7</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Nitrogen</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Chloramine</name>
			<formula>NH<sub>2</sub>Cl</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Commonly used in low concentrations as a disinfectant in municipal water systems as an alternative to chlorination. Water treated with chloramine lacks the distinct <elink ref="17">chlorine</elink> odour of the gaseous treatment and so has improved taste.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Aquarium owners must remove the chloramine from their tap water because it is toxic to fish. Many animals are sensitive to chloramine and it must be removed from water given to many animals in zoos.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Dinitrogen tetroxide</name>
			<formula>N<sub>2</sub>O<sub>4</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>10544-72-6</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp>261.9 K</mp>
			<bp>294.3 K</bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Dinitrogen tetroxide is one of the most important rocket propellants ever developed and by the late 1950s it became the storable oxidizer of choice for rockets in both the USA and USSR.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Nitric oxide</name>
			<formula>NO</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp>109 K</mp>
			<bp>121 K</bp>
			<classes>
				<class>I</class>
			</classes>				
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is an important signaling <glink ref="molecule">molecule</glink> in the body of mammals including humans, one of the few gaseous signaling <glink ref="molecule">molecules</glink> known. It is also a toxic air pollutant produced by automobile engines and power plants.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>The nitric oxide <glink ref="molecule">molecule</glink> is a free radical, which makes it very reactive and unstable. In air, it quickly reacts with <elink ref="8">oxygen</elink> to form the poisonous nitrogen dioxide (NO<sub>2</sub>).</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Nitric dioxide</name>
			<formula>NO<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>10102-44-0</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp>261.95 K</mp>
			<bp>293.25 K</bp>
			<classes>
				<class>HT</class>
			</classes>				
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is one of several nitrogen oxides (NO<sub>x</sub>). This orange/brown gas has a characteristic sharp, biting odor. NO<sub>2</sub> is one of the most prominent air pollutants and a poison by inhalation.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Nitrogen trichloride</name>
			<formula>NCl<sub>3</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>10025-85-1</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp>233 K</mp>
			<bp>344 K</bp>
			<classes>
				<class>E</class>
			</classes>				
			<notes>
				<ptxt>A yellow, oily, pungent-smelling liquid, often found as a byproduct of chemical reactions between nitrogen-containing compounds and <elink ref="17">chlorine</elink>.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Nitrogen trichloride is a very strong explosive; an explosion involving it blinded <blink ref="shd">Sir Humphry Davy</blink> temporarily, and forced him to take on <blink ref="mf">Michael Faraday</blink> as a worker. This was in part because some of Davy's junior lab workers had recently been fired for fighting. Nitrogen trichloride is incredibly sensitive; it will explode upon exposure to cold or hot temperatures, sunlight, or organic substances such as turpentine.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Nitrogen triiodide</name>
			<formula>NI<sub>3</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>13444-85-4</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Also called <elink ref="7">nitrogen</elink> <elink ref="53">iodide</elink>, is a highly explosive compound of <elink ref="7">nitrogen</elink> and iodine. It is a contact explosive, and small quantities explode with a gunpowder-like snap when touched by even a feather, releasing a volatile cloud of iodine vapour.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Small amounts of <elink ref="7">nitrogen</elink> triiodide are sometimes synthesized as a demonstration to chemistry students. However, because the compound is so unstable, it has not been used in blasting caps or primers for explosives.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>The reason for it's instability is due to the size difference between the two different types of atoms. The three iodine atoms are much bigger than the <elink ref="7">nitrogen</elink> atom holding them together. Because of this, not only is the bond between nuclei under much stress and therefore weaker, but the outside electrons of the different iodine atoms are very close, which increases the overall instability of the <glink ref="molecule">molecule</glink>.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Nitrous oxide</name>
			<formula>N<sub>2</sub>O</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp>182.29 K</mp>
			<bp>184.67 K</bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Under room conditions, it is a colourless non-flammable gas, with a pleasant, slightly-sweet odour. It is used in surgery and dentistry for its anaesthetic and analgesic effects, where it is commonly known as laughing gas due to the euphoric effects of inhaling it. It is also used as an oxidizer in internal combustion engines. Nitrous oxide is present in the atmosphere where it acts as a powerful greenhouse gas.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>The gas was discovered by <blink ref="jp">Joseph Priestley</blink> in 1772, who called it phlogisticated nitrous air (see phlogiston). <blink ref="shd">Humphry Davy</blink> in the 1790s tested the gas on himself and some of his friends, including the poets Samuel Taylor Coleridge and Robert Southey. They soon realised that nitrous oxide considerably dulled the sensation of pain, even if the inhaler were still semi-conscious. And so it came into use as an anaesthetic, particularly by dentists, who do not typically have access to the services of an anesthesiologist and who may benefit from a patient who can respond to verbal commands.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Urea phosphate</name>
			<formula>CO(NH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>2</sub>H<sub>3</sub>PO<sub>4</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is made by reacting urea with phosphoric <glink ref="acid">acid</glink> (H<sub>3</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>). It is sometimes used as a fertilizer.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Nitric acid</name>
			<formula>HNO<sub>3</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Nitric acid, otherwise known as aqua fortis or spirit of nitre, is a colourless, corrosive liquid, a toxic <glink ref="acid">acid</glink> which can cause severe burns. If the solution contains more than 86% nitric <glink ref="acid">acid</glink>, it is referred to as fuming nitric <glink ref="acid">acid</glink>, and can be separated into two kinds of fuming <glink ref="acid">acids</glink>, white fuming nitric <glink ref="acid">acid</glink> and red fuming nitric <glink ref="acid">acid</glink>.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Commonly used as a laboratory <glink ref="reagent">reagent</glink>, nitric <glink ref="acid">acid</glink> is used in the manufacture of explosives such as nitroglycerin, trinitrotoluene (TNT) and Cyclotrimethylenetrinitramine (RDX), as well as fertilizers such as ammonium nitrate.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>It has additional uses in metallurgy and refining as it reacts with most metals, and in organic syntheses. When combined with hydrochloric <glink ref="acid">acid</glink>, it forms <glink ref="aquaregia">aqua regia</glink>, one of the few <glink ref="reagent">reagents</glink> capable of dissolving <elink ref="79">gold</elink> and <elink ref="78">platinum</elink>.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>		
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="008" type="3">
	<an>8</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="y">Oxygen</name>	
	<header>
		<ptxt>Oxygen forms compounds with almost all of the other known elements, including some of the rarest, least reactive (<elink ref="54">xenon</elink>; XeO<sub>3</sub>, <elink ref="79">gold</elink>; Au<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>) and synthetic ones.</ptxt>
		<ptxt>The few elements that oxygen will not react with in typical conditions are noble gases - <elink ref="2">helium</elink>, <elink ref="10">neon</elink>, <elink ref="18">argon</elink> and <elink ref="36">krypton</elink>.</ptxt>
	</header>
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Ozone</name>
			<formula>O<sub>3</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>10028-15-6</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp>80.7 K</mp>
			<bp>161.3 K</bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>The highest levels of ozone in the atmosphere are in the stratosphere, in a region also known as the ozone layer between about 10 km and 50 km above the surface. Here it filters out the shorter wavelengths (less than 320 nm) of ultraviolet light (270 to 400 nm) from the Sun that would be harmful to most forms of life in large doses. These same wavelengths are also responsible for the production of vitamin D, which is essential for human health. Ozone in the stratosphere is mostly produced from ultraviolet rays reacting with oxygen.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Ozone can be used for bleaching substances and for killing bacteria. Many municipal drinking water systems kill bacteria with ozone instead of the more common chlorine.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Industrially, ozone or ozonated water is used to; disinfect water before it is bottled; deodorize air and objects, such as after a fire; kill bacteria on food or on contact surfaces; scrub yeast and mold spores from the air in food processing plants; wash fresh fruits and vegetables to kill yeast, mold and bacteria; chemically attack contaminants in water (iron, arsenic, hydrogen sulfide, nitrites, and complex organics lumped together as "colour"); provide an aid to flocculation (agglomeration of <glink ref="molecule">molecules</glink>, which aids in filtration, where the iron and arsenic are removed); clean and bleach fabrics (the latter use is patented); assist in processing plastics to allow adhesion of inks; age rubber samples to determine the useful life of a batch of rubber; in surface water treatment plants to eradicate bacteria such as Giardia and Cryptosporidium.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Water</name>
			<formula>H<sub>2</sub>O</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>7732-18-5</cas>
			<density>0.998 g cm<sup>-3</sup></density>
			<mp>273.15 K</mp>
			<bp>373.124 K</bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt></ptxt>
				<ptxt></ptxt>
				<ptxt></ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>		
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="009" type="6">
	<an>9</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Fluorine</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Hydrofluoric acid</name>
			<formula>HF</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>7664-39-3</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp>189.77</mp>
			<bp>293.15 K</bp>
			<classes>
				<class>HA</class>
				<class>HT</class>
			</classes>		
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Hydrofluoric acid's ability to dissolve oxides makes it important in the purification of both <elink ref="13">aluminium</elink> and <elink ref="92">uranium</elink>. It is also used to etch glass, to remove surface oxides from <elink ref="14">silicon</elink> in the semiconductor industry, as a catalyst for the alkylation of iso-butane and butene in oil refineries and to remove oxide impurities from stainless steel in a process called pickling.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>HF is also used in the synthesis of many fluorine-containing organic compounds, including teflon and refrigerants such as freon.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Fluorite</name>
			<formula>CaF<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is an isometric mineral with a cubic habit, though octahedral and more complex isometric forms are not uncommon.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Fluorite gives its name to the property of fluorescence, as many samples fluoresce strongly in ultra-violet light. The fluorescence may be due to impurities such as yttrium or organic matter in the crystal lattice. Fluorite's fluorescence colour is largely dependent on where the original specimen was located. Blue is the most common colour but red, purple, yellow, green and white also occur. Fluorite also exhibits the property of thermoluminescence.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>As well as ornamental uses, fluorite is used in the making of opalescent glass, enamels for cooking utensils, hydrofluoric <glink ref="acid">acid</glink>, and as a flux in the manufacture of steel. Fluorite is also used in some high performance telescopes and camera lens elements instead of glass. Exposure tools for the semiconductor industry, make the use of fluorite for the optics for 157 nm wavelength. This wavelength is created by an excimer laser with F<sub>2</sub> gas, and the fluorite is a unique material that has high transparency at this wavelength. It has a very low dispersion so light diffraction is far less than ordinary glass, and in telescopes it allows crisp images of astronomical objects even at high power. The name fluorite is derived from the Latin fluo, meaning "flow", in reference to its use as a flux.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="010" type="7">
	<an>10</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Neon</name>
	<header>
		<ptxt>Neon is a noble gas, and therefore generally considered to be inert. However, there is evidence that it may form a compound with <elink ref="9">fluorine</elink>, and there has been growing evidence to show that it can form other compounds. The ions, Ne<sup>+</sup>, (NeAr)<sup>+</sup>, (NeH)<sup>+</sup>, and (HeNe<sup>+</sup>), have been observed from optical and mass spectrometric studies, and neon is also known to form an unstable hydrate.</ptxt>
		<ptxt>No useful or commercial compounds of neon exist at this time.</ptxt>
	</header>
</element>

<element media="y" index="011" type="1">
	<an>11</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Sodium</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Borax</name>
			<formula>Na<sub>2</sub>B<sub>4</sub>O<sub>7</sub> - 10H<sub>2</sub>O</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>1303-96-4</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is a soft white many-sided crystal that dissolves easily in water.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>is widely used in detergents, water softeners, soaps, disinfectants, and pesticides. Its use in detergents is due to its ability to bind to and solvate dirt particles in addition to producing peroxides which have a bleaching effect. One of its most widely advertised uses was as a hand-cleaner for industrial workers. It is used in making enamel glazes, glass and strengthening pottery and ceramics. It is also easily converted to boric <glink ref="acid">acid</glink> or borate, which have many applications. It is also used to make buffer solutions that are used in chemical analysis.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Large amounts of borax pentahydrate (Na<sub>2</sub>B<sub>4</sub>O<sub>7</sub> - 5H<sub>2</sub>O) are used for manufacturing insulating fibreglass and cellulose insulation as a fire retardant and anti-fungal compound. Large amounts are also used in production of sodium perborate monohydrate for use in detergents.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Disodium guanylate(E627)</name>
			<formula>C<sub>10</sub>H<sub>14</sub>N<sub>5</sub>O<sub>8</sub>P</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>A food additive used as a flavour enhancer, derived from dried fish or dried seaweed. It is found in instant noodles, crisps (potato chips) and snacks, savoury rice, tinned vegetables, cured meats, packet soup.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Monosodium methyl arsenate</name>
			<formula>CH<sub>4</sub>AsNaO<sub>3</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>2163-80-6</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<classes>
				<class>T</class>
			</classes>		
			<notes>
				<ptxt>An arsenic-based herbicide and fungicide, one of the most common herbicides used on golf courses.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Sodium benzoate (E211)</name>
			<formula>C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>5</sub>COONa</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>532-32-1</cas>
			<density>1.44</density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>As a food additive it is used as a preservative, effectively killing most yeasts, bacteria and fungi. Sodium benzoate is effective only in acidic conditions (<glink ref="ph">pH</glink> less than 3.6) making its use most prevalent in foods such as preserves, salad dressings (vinegar), carbonated drinks (carbon dioxide), jams (citric <glink ref="acid">acid</glink>), fruit juices (citric <glink ref="acid">acid</glink>), and chinese food sauces (soy, mustard, and duck). It is also found in alcohol-based mouthwash. More recently, sodium benzoate has become apparent in many soft drinks, including Sprite, Sunkist and Dr Pepper.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>It is found naturally in cranberries, prunes, greengage plums, cinnamon, ripe cloves, and apples.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Sodium bicarbonate</name>
			<formula>NaHCO<sub>3</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>144-55-8</cas>
			<density>2.20</density>
			<mp>323.15 K</mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<classes>
				<class>I</class>
			</classes>		
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Also known as sodium hydrogen carbonate, baking soda, bread soda and bicarbonate of soda.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>It is used as an ant<glink ref="acid">acid</glink> to treat <glink ref="acid">acid</glink> indigestion and heartburn. The anhydrous form is also used to absorb moisture and odours; an open box can be left in a refrigerator for this purpose. However, baking soda does not actually absorb odors well when used in a refrigerator.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>When used in toothpaste, baking soda helps to gently remove stains, whiten teeth, freshen breath, and dissolve plaque.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>It is commonly used to increase the pH and total alkalinity of the water for pools and spas. Sodium bicarbonate can be added as a simple solution for restoring the pH balance of water that has a high level of chlorine. </ptxt>
				<ptxt>It also has military applications. Cold sodium bicarbonate can be used to stop the chemical agent White Phosphorus, a common allotrope of phosphorus often used in incendiary bullets, from spreading inside a soldier's afflicted wounds.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Sodium carbonate</name>
			<formula>Na<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>497-19-8</cas>
			<density>2.5</density>
			<mp>1124 K</mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Used in the manufacture of glass, pulp and paper, detergents, and chemicals such as sodium silicates and sodium phosphates.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>It is used as a water softener during laundry. It competes with the ions magnesium and calcium in hard water and prevents them from bonding with the detergent being used. Without using washing soda, additional detergent is needed to soak up the magnesium and calcium ions. Called washing soda in the detergent section of stores, it effectively removes oil, grease, and alcohol stains.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>When used in toothpaste, baking soda helps to gently remove stains, whiten teeth, freshen breath, and dissolve plaque.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Sodium carbonate is widely used in photographic processes as a <glink ref="ph">pH</glink> regulator to maintain stable alkaline conditions necessary for the action of the majority of developing agents, it is also used by the brick industry as a wetting agent to reduce the amount of water needed to extrude the clay.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Sodium Chloride</name>
			<formula>NaCl</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>7647-14-5</cas>
			<density>1.18</density>
			<mp>1074 K</mp>
			<bp>1738 K</bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Sodium chloride, also known as common salt, table salt, or halite. Sodium chloride is the salt most responsible for the salinity of the ocean and of the extracellular fluid of many multicellular organisms.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>It is essential to life on Earth. Most biological tissues and body fluids contain a varying amount of salt. The concentration of sodium ions in the blood is directly related to the regulation of safe body-fluid levels. Propagation of nerve impulses by signal transduction is regulated by sodium ions. (Potassium, a metal closely related to Sodium, is also a major component in the same bodily systems).</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Sodium citrate</name>
			<formula>Na<sub>3</sub>C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>5</sub>O<sub>7</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Is chiefly used as a food additive, usually for flavour or as a preservative. Sodium citrate is common in lemon-lime soft drinks, and it is partly what causes them to have their sour taste.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Sodium cyanide</name>
			<formula>NaCN</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>143-33-9</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp>837 K</mp>
			<bp>1496 K</bp>
			<classes>
				<class>HT</class>
			</classes>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Like the similar potassium cyanide, NaCN has a smell like bitter almonds, but not everyone can smell it.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Sodium cyanide is used to extract gold and other precious metals from ore, and so metal mining operations consume most of the sodium cyanide production. Sodium cyanide is illegally used to collect fish. Accidents with cyanide solutions are a severe danger to aquatic ecosystems.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Cyanide salts are among the most rapidly acting of all known poisons. Cyanide is a potent inhibitor of respiration.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Sodium dodecyl sulfate</name>
			<formula>CH<sub>3</sub>(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>11</sub>OSO<sub>3</sub>Na</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp>479 K</mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Also known as sodium lauryl sulfate (SLS), is an ionic surfactant that is used in household products such as toothpastes, shampoos, shaving foams and bubble baths for its thickening effect and its ability to create a lather.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Like all detergent surfactants (including soaps), it removes oils from the skin, and can cause skin irritation. It is also irritating to the eyes.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>It is suspected that SLS is linked to a number of skin issues such as dermatitis, and when combined with certain chemicals, SLS may become a <glink ref="carcinogen">carcinogen</glink>.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Sodium fluoride</name>
			<formula>NaF</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>7681-49-4</cas>
			<density>2.558</density>
			<mp>1266 K</mp>
			<bp>1973 K</bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Once used to fluoridate water, an ingredient in toothpaste that prevents cavities.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Sodium iodide</name>
			<formula>NaI</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>7681-82-5</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp>933 K</mp>
			<bp>1577 K</bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Sodium <elink ref="53">iodide</elink> is commonly used to treat and prevent iodine deficiency. Solid crystals can be used to detect radiation (e.g. radiation from <elink ref="92">uranium</elink>) - a solid crystal of <elink ref="11">sodium</elink> <elink ref="53">iodide</elink> creates a pulse of light when radiation interacts with it.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Sodium hypochlorite</name>
			<formula>NaOCl</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>7681-52-9</cas>
			<density>1.18</density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>A solution of sodium hypochlorite is frequently used as a disinfectant and as a bleaching agent; indeed, often it is simply called "bleach", though other chemicals are sometimes given that name as well.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Sodium metabisulfite</name>
			<formula>Na<sub>2</sub>S<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is used as a food additive, mainly as a preservative and is sometimes identified as E223. As an additive, it may cause allergic reactions, particularly skin irritation, gastric irritation and asthma. It is not recommended for consumption by children.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>It is commonly used in homebrewing preparations to sanitize equipment.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Sodium monofluorophosphate</name>
			<formula>Na<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>3</sub>F</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Best known as an ingredient in toothpastes for both humans and animals. It is claimed to protect tooth enamel from attack by bacteria that cause dental caries (cavities). Though developed by a chemist at Procter and Gamble, its use in toothpaste (Colgate toothpaste) was patented by Colgate-Palmolive, as Procter and Gamble was engaged in the marketing of Crest toothpaste (containing stannous fluoride).</ptxt>
				<ptxt>It is also used in some medications for the treatment of osteoporosis.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Sodium nitrate</name>
			<formula>NaNO<sub>3</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>7631-99-4</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp>580 K</mp>
			<bp>653 K</bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Best known as an ingredient in toothpastes for both humans and animals. It is claimed to protect tooth enamel from attack by bacteria that cause dental caries (cavities). Though developed by a chemist at Procter and Gamble, its use in toothpaste (Colgate toothpaste) was patented by Colgate-Palmolive, as Procter and Gamble was engaged in the marketing of Crest toothpaste (containing stannous fluoride).</ptxt>
				<ptxt>It can be used in the production of nitric <glink ref="acid">acid</glink> by combining with sulfuric <glink ref="acid">acid</glink> and subsequent separation through fractional distillation of the nitric <glink ref="acid">acid</glink>, leaving behind a residue of sodium bisulfate.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Sodium nitrite</name>
			<formula>NaNO<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>7631-99-4</cas>
			<density>2.2</density>
			<mp>543 K</mp>
			<bp>593 K</bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>As a food additive, it serves a dual purpose in the food industry since it both alters the colour of preserved fish and meats and also prevents growth of Clostridium botulinum, the bacteria which causes botulism. In the European Union it may be used only as a mixture with salt containing at most 0.6 % sodium nitrite. It has the E number E250.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Various dangers of using this chemical as a food additive have been suggested and researched by scientists, although no conclusive evidence has been put forth. A principal concern is the formation of carcinogenic N-nitrosamines by reaction with sodium nitrite; other ingredients are often added to prevent nitrosamine-generating reactions.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Sodium nitrite also has been used in human and veterinary medicine as a vasodilator, a bronchodilator, an intestinal relaxant or a laxative, and an antidote for cyanide poisoning.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Sodium persulfate</name>
			<formula>Na<sub>2</sub>S<sub>2</sub>O<sub>8</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>7775-27-1</cas>
			<density>2.40</density>
			<mp>543 K</mp>
			<bp>593 K</bp>
			<classes>
				<class>I</class>
			</classes>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is used as a bleach, both standalone (particularly in hair cosmetics) and as a detergent component. It is a replacement for ammonium persulfate in etching mixtures for zinc and printed circuit boards, and is used for pickling of copper and some other metals. It is a source of free radicals, making it useful as an initiator for eg. emulsion polymerization reactions and for accelerated curing of low formaldehyde adhesives. It is also used as a soil conditioner and in manufacture of dyestuffs, modification of starch, bleach activator, desizing agent for oxidative desizing.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Sodium propionate</name>
			<formula>Na(C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>5</sub>COO)</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>137-40-6</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp>562 K</mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Used as a mold inhibitor in bakery products.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Sodium pyrophosphate</name>
			<formula>Na(C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>5</sub>COO)</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>137-40-6</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp>562 K</mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<classes>
				<class>MT</class>
				<class>MI</class>
			</classes>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Sodium pyrophosphate is used as a buffer, an emulsifier, and a thickening agent, and is often used as a food additive. Common foods containing sodium pyrophosphate include chicken nuggets, marshmallows, crab meat, imitation crab, and soy-based meat alternatives.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>In toothpaste, sodium pyrophosphate acts as a tartar control agent, serving to remove <elink ref="20">calcium</elink> and <elink ref="12">magnesium</elink> from saliva and thus preventing them from being deposited on teeth. Sodium pyrophosphate is sometimes used in household detergents to prevent similar deposition on clothing, but due to its phosphate content it causes eutrophication of water, promoting algae growth.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Sodium selenite</name>
			<formula>Na<sub>2</sub>Se)<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>10102-18-8</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<classes>
				<class>T</class>
			</classes>
			<notes>
				<ptxt> It is a source of selenium in many food supplements. Although <elink ref="34">selenium</elink> is poisonous, it should be noted that selenium is essential in small amounts. Humans and animals require selenium for the function of a number of selenium-dependent enzymes, also known as selenoproteins.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Sodium silicoaluminate</name>
			<formula></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>1344-00-9</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Anticaking agent added to various products including table salt and other food products, powders, and house paints to prevent the formation of large crystals or lumps.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Sodium stearate</name>
			<formula>C<sub>17</sub>H<sub>35</sub>COONa</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>The major component of soap.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Sodium sulfite</name>
			<formula>Na<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>3</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp>525 K</mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is primarily used in the pulp and paper industry. It is used in water treatment as an <elink ref="8">oxygen</elink> scavenger agent, in the photographic industry to protect developer solutions from oxidation and (as hypo clear solution) to wash fixer (sodium thiosulfate) from film and photo-paper emulsions, in textile industry as a bleaching, as a desulfurizing and as a dechlorinating agent and in leather trade for the sulfitization of tanning extracts.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>It is also used as a preservative to prevent dried fruit from discolouring, and for preserving meats.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Sodium thiopental</name>
			<formula>C<sub>11</sub>H<sub>17</sub>N<sub>2</sub>NaO<sub>2</sub>S</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Thiopental is an ultra-short acting barbiturate and is most commonly used in the induction phase of general anesthesia. Following intravenous injection the drug rapidly reaches the brain and causes unconsciousness within 30-45 seconds. At one minute, the drug attains a peak concentration of about 60% of the total dose in the brain. Thereafter, the drug distributes to the rest of the body and in about 5-10 minutes the concentration is low enough in the brain such that consciousness returns.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Along with pancuronium bromide and potassium chloride, thiopental is used in 37 states of the US to execute prisoners by lethal injection. A megadose is given which places the patient into a rapidly induced coma. Executions using the three drug combination are usually effective in approximately 10 minutes, but have been known to take several times this length. The use of thiopental alone is hypothesized to cause death in approximately 45 minutes.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Thiopental is still used in some places as a truth serum. The barbiturate drugs as a class decrease higher cortical brain functioning. Psychiatrist hypothesize that lying is more complex than the truth, suppression of the higher cortical functions may lead to the uncovering of the "truth" since the "truth" would theoretically be less complex.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Sodium thiopental</name>
			<formula>Na<sub>5</sub>P<sub>3</sub>O<sub>10</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is used in various applications such as a preservative for seafood, meats, poultry and pet foods. It is also used in toothpaste and as a builder in soaps and detergents, improving their cleansing ability.</ptxt>				
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="012" type="4">
	<an>12</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Magnesium</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Magnesium carbonate</name>
			<formula>MgCO<sub>3</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density>2.958</density>
			<mp>935 K</mp>
			<bp></bp>	
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Used in flooring, fireproofing, fire extinguishing compositions, cosmetics, dusting powder, and toothepaste. Other applications are as filler material, smoke suppressant in plastics, a reinforcing agent in neoprene rubber, a drying agent, and colour retention in floods. In addition, high purity magnesium carbonate is used as antacid and as an additive in table salt to keep it free flowing.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Magnesium chloride</name>
			<formula>MgCl<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>7786-30-3</cas>
			<density>2.32</density>
			<mp>987 K</mp>
			<bp>1685 K</bp>	
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is used in the manufacture of textiles, paper, fireproofing agents, cements and refrigeration brine.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Magnesium chloride is an important coagulant used in the preparation of tofu from soy milk. In Japan it is sold as nigari (the term is derived from the Japanese word for "bitter"), a white powder produced from seawater after the sodium chloride has been removed, and the water evaporated. Nigari consists mostly of magnesium chloride, with some magnesium sulfate and other trace elements.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Magnesium diboride</name>
			<formula>MgB<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>12007-25-9</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>	
			<notes>
				<ptxt>An inexpensive and simple superconductor that can be synthesized by high temperature reaction between <elink ref="5">boron</elink> and magnesium.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Magnesium hydroxide</name>
			<formula>Mg(OH)<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density>2.4</density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>	
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Otherwise known as milk of magnesia, is commonly used as an antacid or a laxative. The mineral form of magnesium hydroxide is known as brucite. Magnesium hydroxide interferes with the absorption of folic <glink ref="acid">acid</glink> and <elink ref="26">iron</elink>. The diarrhea caused by magnesium hydroxide carries away much of the body's supply of potassium, and failure to take extra potassium will lead to muscle cramps.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Magnesium oxide</name>
			<formula>Mg(OH)<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density>0.00358</density>
			<mp>3073 K</mp>
			<bp>3873 K</bp>	
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is used by many libraries for preserving/deacidifying books, and as an insulator in industrial cables. It is also used as a medication to relieve heartburn, sour stomach, or acid indigestion. Medical uses of Magnesium oxide also include using it as a short-term laxative, or used to supplement a diet with magnesium. Magnesium oxide is a principle ingredient in construction materials used for fireproofing.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Magnesium peroxide</name>
			<formula>MgO<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Magnesium peroxide being environmentally benign and its stable <elink ref="8">oxygen</elink> release are used widely in the cosmetic, agricultural, pharmaceutical, and environmental industries. It is used to reduce contaminant levels in groundwater. Magnesium peroxide is used in the bioremediation of contaminated soil and can improve the soil quality for plant growth and metabolism. It also used in the aquaculture industry for bioremediation.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Magnesium stearate</name>
			<formula>C<sub>36</sub>H<sub>70</sub>MgO<sub>4</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>557-04-0</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>	
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is often used as a filling agent in the manufacture of medical pills. In this regard, the substance is also useful because it has lubricating properties, preventing ingredients from sticking to manufacturing equipment during the compression of chemical powders into solid pills. It is also a common ingredient in baby powders. In pure powder form, the substance can be a dust explosion hazard, although this issue is effectively moot beyond the manufacturing plants using it.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Magnesium sulfate (Epsom Salt)</name>
			<formula>MgSO<sub>4</sub>.7H<su>2</su>O</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>10034-99-8</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Epsom salt was originally prepared by boiling down mineral waters at Epsom, England and afterwards prepared from sea water.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>In agriculture and gardening, magnesium sulfate is used to correct magnesium deficiency in soil (magnesium is an essential element in the chlorophyll <glink ref="molecule">molecule</glink>). It is most commonly applied to potted plants, or to magnesium-hungry crops, such as potatoes, roses, and tomatoes. The advantage of magnesium sulfate over other magnesium soil amendments (such as dolomitic lime) is its high solubility.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Locally it may be used as a treatment of an ingrown nail. Oral magnesium sulfate, or magnesium oxide, is used as a laxative. Epsom salts are also available in a gel form for topical application in treating aches and pains. Intravenous use is broadening, as magnesium sulfate reduces striated muscle contractions and blocks peripheral neuromuscular transmission by reducing acetylcholine release at the myoneural junction, as well as other effects.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="013" type="5">
	<an>13</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Aluminium</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Aluminium boride</name>
			<formula>AlB<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>12041-50-8</cas>
			<density>3.19</density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is used as a grinding compound to replace <elink ref="6">diamond</elink> or corundum. It is also used as a coating to strengthen <elink ref="13">aluminium</elink>.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Aluminium chlorohydrate</name>
			<formula>Al<sub>n</sub>Cl<sub>(3n-m)</sub>(OH)<sub>m</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>A group of aluminium salts used in deodorants and antiperspirants and as a flocculant in water purification.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Aluminium gallium indium phosphide</name>
			<formula>AlGaInP</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>A semiconductor material used in the manufacture of light-emitting diodes of high-brightness red, orange, green, and yellow colour, to form the heterostructure emitting light. It is also used to make diode lasers.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Aluminium gallium nitride</name>
			<formula>AlGaN</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Used to manufacture light-emitting diodes operating in blue to ultraviolet region, where wavelengths down to 250 nm (far UV) were achieved. It is also used in blue semiconductor lasers. It is also used in detectors of ultraviolet radiation.</ptxt>				
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Aluminium gallium phosphide</name>
			<formula>AlGaP</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>A semiconductor material used in the manufacture of green light-emitting diodes.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Aluminium monostearate</name>
			<formula>Al(OH)<sub>2</sub>C<sub>18</sub>H<sub>35</sub>O<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is used to form gels in the packaging of pharmaceuticals, and in the preparation of variuos colours for cosmetics. It is usually safe in commercial products, but aluminium may accumulate in the body.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Aluminium nitrate</name>
			<formula>Al(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>17473-90-0</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp>346.89 K</mp>
			<bp>375 K</bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is used in tanning leather, antiperspirants, corrosion inhibitors, extraction of <elink ref="92">uranium</elink>, petroleum refining, and as a nitrating agent.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Aluminium sulfate</name>
			<formula>Al<sub>2</sub>(SO<sub>4</sub>)<sub>3</sub>.16H<sub>2</sub>O</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>16828-11-8</cas>
			<density>2.71</density>
			<mp>1043 K</mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Used in water purification and as a mordant in dyeing and printing textiles. In water purification, it causes impurities to coagulate which are removed as the particulate settles to the bottom of the container or more easily filtered.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>When dissolved in a large amount of neutral or slightly-alkaline water, aluminum sulfate produces a gelatinous precipitate of aluminum hydroxide, Al(OH)<sub>3</sub>. In dyeing and printing cloth, the gelatinous precipitate helps the dye adhere to the clothing fibers by rendering the pigment insoluble.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Yttrium aluminium garnet</name>
			<formula>Y<sub>3</sub>Al<sub>5</sub>O<sub>12</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>A synthetic crystalline material of the garnet group, used as the active laser medium in various solid-state lasers..</ptxt>
				<ptxt>It also finds use in jewellery as a diamond simulant. Coloured variants are faceted and valued (as synthetics) for their clarity, durability, high refractive index and dispersion.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="014" type="0">
	<an>14</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Silicon</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Molybdenum(IV) silicide</name>
			<formula>MoSi<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>12136-78-6</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp>2503 K</mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Molybdenum disilicide heating elements can be used for temperatures up to 1800&degree;C (2073 K), in electric furnaces used in laboratory and production environment in production of glass, steel, electronics, ceramics, and in heat treatment of materials. While the elements are brittle, they can operate at high power without aging, and their electrical resistivity does not increase with operation time.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Polydimethylsiloxane</name>
			<formula>(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>SiO[SiO(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>]nSi(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>63148-62-9</cas>
			<density>0.965</density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is the primary component in Silly Putty. The rubbery, vinegary-smelling silicone caulks, adhesives, and aquarium sealants are also well-known. PDMS is also used as a component in silicone grease and other silicone based lubricants, as well as in defoaming agents, damping fluids, heat transfer fluids, cosmetics, hair conditioner and other applications. PDMS has also been used as a filler fluid in breast implants, although this practice has decreased somewhat, due to safety concerns. It continues to be used in knuckle replacement implants, with good results.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>As a food additive, it has the E number E900 and is used as an anti-foaming agent and an anti-caking agent.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Platinum silicide</name>
			<formula>PtSi</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is used in detectors for infrared astronomy.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Silicon-germanium</name>
			<formula>SiGe</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>63148-62-9</cas>
			<density>0.965</density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>This semiconductor material is commonly used in the integrated circuit manufacturing industry.</ptxt>				
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Silane</name>
			<formula>SiH<sub>4</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>7803-62-5</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp>88 K</mp>
			<bp>161 K</bp>
			<classes>
				<class>I</class>
			</classes>		
			<notes>
				<ptxt>At room temperature, silane is a gas, and is <glink ref="pyrophoric">pyrophoric</glink> - it undergoes spontaneous combustion in air, without the need for external ignition.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Several industrial and medical applications exist for silanes. For instance, silanes are used as coupling agents to adhere glass fibres to a polymer matrix, stabilizing the composite material. They can also be used to couple a bio-inert layer on a <elink ref="22">titanium</elink> implant. Other applications include water repellents, masonary protection, control of graffiti, applying polycrystalline silicon layers on silicon wafers when manufacturing semiconductors, and sealants.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Silicon carbide</name>
			<formula>SiC</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>409-21-2</cas>
			<density>3.22</density>
			<mp>2973 K</mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>The word moissanite is a trade name given to silicon carbide for use in the gem business.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Silicon carbide is used for blue LEDs, ultrafast Schottky diodes, MESFETs and high temperature IGBTs and thyristors for high power switching. Due to its high thermal conductivity, SiC is also used as substrate for other semiconductor materials such as gallium nitride.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Silicon carbide's hardness and rigidity make it a desirable mirror material for astronomical work, although they also make manufacturing and figuring such mirrors quite difficult.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Silicon-infiltrated carbon-carbon composite is used for high performance brake discs as it is able to withstand extreme temperatures. The silicon reacts with the graphite in the carbon-carbon composite to become silicon carbide. These discs are used on some sports cars.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Silicon dioxide (silica)</name>
			<formula>SiO<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>14808-60-7</cas>
			<density>2.6</density>
			<mp>1983 K</mp>
			<bp>2503 K</bp>
			<classes>
				<class>SC</class>
			</classes>		
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Silica is found in nature in several forms, including quartz and opal. Inexpensive soda-lime glass is the most common and typically found in drinking glasses, bottles, and windows. The ceramic re-entry heat protection tiles mounted on the bottom side of the Space Shuttles are made mostly of silica (see HRSI), as are the firebricks used in steel processing.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Silica, along with alumina (silica-alumina), forms a major part of the crystal lattice of clay minerals. These decompose on firing and form part of the microstructure of clay based ceramics such as earthenware, stoneware and porcelain.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Silica is also used as a food additive, primarily as a flow agent in powdered foods, or to absorb water.</ptxt>
				<ptxt></ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Silicon nitride</name>
			<formula>Si<sub>3</sub>N<sub>4</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>12033-89-5</cas>
			<density>3.44</density>
			<mp>2173 K</mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Silicon nitride is the main component in silicon nitride ceramics, which have relatively good shock resistance compared to other ceramics. Rollers made of silicon nitride ceramic are sometimes used in high-end skateboard bearings, due to the material's shock and heat-resistant characteristics. Also used an ignition source for domestic gas appliances, Hot Surface Ignition.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="015" type="3">
	<an>15</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="y">Phosphorus</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Alendronate</name>
			<formula>C<sub>4</sub>H<sub>18</sub>NNaO<sub>10</sub>P<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>121268-17-5</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Used for the treatment of osteoporosis and several other bone diseases.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Calcium phosphide</name>
			<formula>Ca<sub>3</sub>P<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp>1873 K</mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Used in incendiary bombs, fireworks, torpedoes, self-igniting naval pyrotechnic flares, and various water-activated ammunition..</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Gallium(III) phosphide</name>
			<formula>GaP</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Used for manufacture of low and standard brightness red, orange, and green light-emitting diodes (LED). It is a low-cost material. GaP has been used as an LED material since the 1960s. It has a relatively short life at higher current and its lifetime is sensitive to temperature. It is used standalone or together with gallium arsenide phosphide.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Glyphosate</name>
			<formula>C<sub>3</sub>H<sub>8</sub>NO<sub>5</sub>P</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>A non-selective herbicide to kill weeds, especially perennials. Many crops have been genetically engineered to be resistant to it. The chemical is only absorbed by the leaves of plants and it is not absorbed by roots from the soil.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Ibandronic acid</name>
			<formula>C<sub>9</sub>H<sub>23</sub>NO<sub>7</sub>P<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>114084-78-5</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Used in the prevention and treatment of osteoporosis. It may also be used to treat hypercalcemia.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Phosphine</name>
			<formula>PH<sub>3</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>7803-51-2</cas>
			<density>1.379</density>
			<mp>139 K</mp>
			<bp>185.2 K</bp>
			<classes>
				<class>HF</class>
				<class>HT</class>
			</classes>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Phosphine is highly toxic; it can easily kill in relatively low concentrations. Because of this, the gas is used for pest control by fumigation. For farm use, it is often sold in the form of <elink ref="13">aluminium</elink> phosphide, <elink ref="20">calcium</elink> phosphide, or <elink ref="30">zinc</elink> phosphide pellets, which yield phosphine on contact with atmospheric water or rodents' stomach <glink ref="acid">acid</glink>. These pellets also contain other chemicals which evolve ammonia which helps to reduce the potential for spontaneous ignition or explosion of the phosphine gas. They may also contain other agents, such as methanethiol, to give the gas a detectable garlic smell to help warn against its presence in the atmosphere.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Phosphine is also used as a dopant in the semiconductor industry.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Sarin</name>
			<formula>C<sub>4</sub>H<sub>10</sub>FO<sub>2</sub>P</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp>217 K</mp>
			<bp>431 K</bp>
			<classes>				
				<class>HT</class>
			</classes>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>An extremely toxic substance whose sole application is as a nerve agent. As a chemical weapon, it is classified as a weapon of mass destruction by the United Nations according to UN Resolution 687, and its production and stockpiling was outlawed by the Chemical Weapons Convention of 1993.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Tricalcium phosphate</name>
			<formula>Ca<sub>3</sub>(PO<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density>3.14</density>
			<mp>1670 K</mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<classes>
				<class>I</class>
			</classes>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>An important raw material for the production of phosphoric <glink ref="acid">acid</glink> and fertilizers. Calcium phosphate is also a raising agent (food additives) E341. Is a mineral salt found in rocks and bones, it is used in cheese products.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>It is also used as a nutritional supplement. There is some debate about the different bioavailabilities of the different calcium salts. It is commonly used in porcelain and dental powders, and medically as an antacid or calcium supplement, although calcium carbonate is more common in this regard.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="016" type="3">
	<an>16</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="y">Sulfur</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Sulfamic acid</name>
			<formula>H<sub>3</sub>NO<sub>3</sub>S</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>5329-14-6</cas>
			<densityl>2.15</densityl>
			<mp>478 K</mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<classes>
				<class>C</class>
				<class>T</class>
			</classes>		
			<notes>
				<ptxt>The most famous applicaton of sulfamic <glink ref="acid">acid</glink> is in the synthesis of compounds that taste sweet. It is used as an acidic cleaning agent, typically for metals and ceramics. It is a replacement for hydrochloric <glink ref="acid">acid</glink> for the removal of rust.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>It's other uses include; catalyst for esterification process, dye and pigment manufacturing, herbicide, coagulator for urea-formaldehyde resins, ingredient in fire extinguishing media, in the pulp and paper industry as a chloride stabilizer and for the synthesis of nitrous oxide by reaction with nitric <glink ref="acid">acid</glink>.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Sulfur dioxide</name>
			<formula>SO<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>7446-09-5</cas>
			<densityl></densityl>
			<mp>200.75 K</mp>
			<bp>263 K</bp>
			<classes>
				<class>T</class>
			</classes>		
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is produced by volcanoes and in various industrial processes. In particular, poor-quality coal and petroleum contain sulfur compounds, and generate sulfur dioxide when burned: the gas reacts with water and atmospheric <elink ref="8">oxygen</elink> to form sulfuric <glink ref="acid">acid</glink> (H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>) and thus <glink ref="acid">acid</glink> rain.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Sulfur dioxide is sometimes used as a preservative in alcoholic drinks, or dried apricots and other dried fruits. The preservative is used to maintain the appearance of the fruit rather than prevent rotting. This can give fruit a distinctive chemical taste. Prior to the development of Freons, sulfur dioxide was used as a refrigerant in home refrigerators.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Sulfuric Acid</name>
			<formula>H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>7664-93-9</cas>
			<densityl>1.84</densityl>
			<mp>283 K</mp>
			<bp>610 K</bp>
			<classes>
				<class>HA</class>
				<class>T</class>
			</classes>		
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Sulfuric <glink ref="acid">acid</glink> has many applications, and is produced in greater amounts than any other chemical besides water. World production in 2001 was 165 million tonnes. Principal uses include ore processing, fertilizer manufacturing, oil refining, wastewater processing, and chemical synthesis.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Sulfuric <glink ref="acid">acid</glink> is produced in the upper atmosphere of Venus by the sun's photochemical action on <elink ref="6">carbon</elink> dioxide, sulfur dioxide, and water vapour. Ultraviolet photons of wavelengths less than 169 nm can photodissociate carbon dioxide into carbon monoxide and atomic <elink ref="8">oxygen</elink>. Atomic <elink ref="8">oxygen</elink> is highly reactive; when it reacts with sulfur dioxide, a trace component of the Venusian atmosphere, the result is sulfur trioxide, which can combine with water vapour, another trace component of Venus' atmosphere, to yield sulfuric <glink ref="acid">acid</glink>.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="017" type="6">
	<an>17</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Chlorine</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Calcium hypochlorite</name>
			<formula>Ca(ClO)<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is widely used for water treatment (drinking water or swimming pools) and as a bleaching agent (bleaching powder). This chemical is considered to be relatively stable and has greater available chlorine than sodium hypochlorite (liquid bleach).</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Hydrochloric acid</name>
			<formula>HCl</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>7647-01-0</cas>
			<density>1.18</density>
			<mp>247 K</mp>
			<bp>383 K</bp>
			<classes>
				<class>HA</class>
			</classes>		
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Hydrochloric <glink ref="acid">acid</glink> is a strong inorganic <glink ref="acid">acid</glink> that is used in many industrial processes.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>The largest hydrochloric <glink ref="acid">acid</glink> consumption is in the production of organic compounds such as vinyl chloride for PVC, and MDI and TDI for polyurethane. This is often captive use, consuming locally-produced hydrochloric acid that never actually reaches the open market. Other organic compounds produced with hydrochloric acid include bisphenol A for polycarbonate, activated carbon, and ascorbic acid, as well as numerous pharmaceutical products.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Hydrochloric acid is a fundamental chemical, and as such it is used for a large number of small-scale applications, such as leather processing, household cleaning, and building construction. In addition, a way of stimulating oil production is by injecting hydrochloric <glink ref="acid">acid</glink> into the rock formation of an oil well, dissolving a portion of the rock, and creating a large-pore structure. Oil-well acidizing is a common process in the North Sea oil production industry.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Many chemical reactions involving hydrochloric acid are applied in the production of food, food ingredients, and food additives. Typical products include aspartame, fructose, citric acid, lysine, hydrolyzed (vegetable) protein as food enhancer, and in gelatin production. Food-grade (extra-pure) hydrochloric acid can be applied when needed for the final product. Mixing simple <elink ref="13">aluminium</elink> foil with hydrochloric <glink ref="acid">acid</glink> produces <elink ref="1">hydrogen</elink>. The <elink ref="1">hydrogen</elink> can then be stored in a balloon. Upon application of a flame to the balloon it will produce a fiery explosion.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Chlorine dioxide</name>
			<formula>ClO<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>10049-04-4</cas>
			<density>1.642</density>
			<mp>214 K</mp>
			<bp>283 K</bp>
			<classes>
				<class>O</class>
				<class>HT</class>
			</classes>		
			<notes>
				<ptxt>A reddish-yellow gas which is one of several known oxides of chlorine. Chlorine dioxide is not stable in the gas state above 15% volume in air at <glink ref="stp">STP</glink> and can spontaneously and explosively decompose into chlorine and <elink ref="8">oxygen</elink>.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Chlorine dioxide is used primarily (95%+) for bleaching of wood pulp, but is also used for the bleaching of flour and for the disinfection of water. Chlorine dioxide is also used in conjunction with ozone disinfection of water to reduce the formation of bromates which are regulated <glink ref="carcinogen">carcinogens</glink>.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>It is more effective than chlorine against viruses, bacteria and protozoa </ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Sodium Chloride</name>
			<formula>NaCl</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>7647-14-5</cas>
			<density>1.18</density>
			<mp>1074 K</mp>
			<bp>1738 K</bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Sodium chloride, also known as common salt, table salt, or halite. Sodium chloride is the salt most responsible for the salinity of the ocean and of the extracellular fluid of many multicellular organisms.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>It is essential to life on Earth. Most biological tissues and body fluids contain a varying amount of salt. The concentration of sodium ions in the blood is directly related to the regulation of safe body-fluid levels. Propagation of nerve impulses by signal transduction is regulated by sodium ions. (Potassium, a metal closely related to Sodium, is also a major component in the same bodily systems).</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Sodium hypochlorite</name>
			<formula>NaOCl</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>7681-52-9</cas>
			<density>1.18</density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>A solution of sodium hypochlorite is frequently used as a disinfectant and as a bleaching agent; indeed, often it is simply called "bleach", though other chemicals are sometimes given that name as well.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="018" type="7">
	<an>18</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Argon</name>
	<header>
		<ptxt>Argon is a noble gas, and therefore generally considered to be inert.</ptxt>
		<ptxt>In August 2000, the first argon compounds were formed by researchers at the University of Helsinki. By shining ultraviolet light onto frozen argon containing a small amount of <elink ref="1">hydrogen</elink> <elink ref="9">fluoride</elink>, argon hydrofluoride (HArF) was formed. It is stable up to 40K (-233&degree;C). The discovery of argon difluoride (ArF<sub>2</sub>) was announced in 2003.</ptxt>
		<ptxt>No useful or commercial compounds of argon exist at this time.</ptxt>
	</header>
</element>

<element media="y" index="019" type="1">
	<an>19</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Potassium</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Potassium alginate</name>
			<formula>KC<sub>6</sub>H<sub>7</sub>O<sub>6</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is an extract of seaweed and is used as a thickener in the food industry and as a gelling agent and emulsifier.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Potassium benzoate</name>
			<formula></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>A food preservative that inhibits the growth of mold, yeast and some bacteria. It works best in low-<glink ref="ph">pH</glink> products, below 4.5, where it exists as benzoic <glink ref="acid">acid</glink>. Acidic food and beverage like fruit juice (citric <glink ref="acid">acid</glink>), sparkling drinks (<elink ref="6">carbon</elink> <elink ref="8">dioxide</elink>), soft drinks (phosphoric <glink ref="acid">acid</glink>), pickles (vinegar) or other acidified food are preserved with potassium benzoate.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Potassium chlorate</name>
			<formula>KClO<sub>3</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>3811-04-9</cas>
			<density>2.32</density>
			<mp>629 K</mp>
			<bp>673 K</bp>
			<classes>
				<class>O</class>
			</classes>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is used in some recipes for gunpowder, generally replacing the less powerful ingredient potassium nitrate. Potassium chlorate is used also as a pesticide.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Potassium chlorate is used in the oxygen-supply systems of aircraft, and has been responsible for at least one plane crash. A fire on the space station MIR was also traced to this substance. The decomposition of potassium chlorate was also used to provide the <elink ref="8">oxygen</elink> supply for limelights.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Potassium chloride</name>
			<formula>KCl</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>7447-40-7</cas>
			<density>1.987</density>
			<mp>1049 K</mp>
			<bp>1770 K</bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>The majority of the potassium chloride produced is used for making fertilizer[2], since the growth of many plants is limited by their potassium intake. As a chemical feedstock it is used for the manufacture of potassium hydroxide and potassium metal. It is also used in medicine, scientific applications, food processing, as a sodium-free substitute for table salt (sodium chloride), and in judicial execution through lethal injection.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Potassium cyanate</name>
			<formula>KCNO</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>590-28-3</cas>
			<density>2.05</density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is a general chemical <glink ref="reagent">reagent</glink> and it is used as a herbicide.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Potassium fluoride</name>
			<formula>KF</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>7789-23-3</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Used for etching glass and also as a preservative and insecticide.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Potassium nitrate</name>
			<formula>KNO<sub>3</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>7757-79-1</cas>
			<density>2.1</density>
			<mp>607 K</mp>
			<bp>673 K</bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>One of the most useful applications of potassium nitrate is in the production of nitric <glink ref="acid">acid</glink>, by adding concentrated sulfuric <glink ref="acid">acid</glink> to an aqueous solution of potassium nitrate, yielding nitric <glink ref="acid">acid</glink> and potassium sulfate which are separated through fractional distillation.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>is also used as a fertilizer, in model rocket propellant, and in several fireworks such as smoke bombs, in which a mixture with sugar produces a smoke cloud of 600 times their own volume.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>In the process of food preservation, potassium nitrate is a common ingredient of salted meat, but heart patients need to take care with it. As a preservative it can be known as E249.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>It has also been used in the manufacture of ice cream and can be found in some toothpastes for sensitive teeth. Recently, the use of potassium nitrate in toothpastes for sensitive teeth has increased dramatically, despite the fact that it has not been conclusively shown to help dental hypersensitivity.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Potassium sorbat</name>
			<formula>C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>7</sub>O<sub>2</sub>K</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Used to inhibit molds, and yeasts in many foods, such as cheese, wine, yogurt, and baked goods. It can also be found in the ingredients list of many dried fruit products. In addition, herbal dietary supplement products generally contain potassium sorbate, which acts to prevent mold and microbes and to increase shelf life, and is used in such tiny quantities that there is no known adverse health effect. Labeling of this preservative can either read as "potassium sorbate," or "sorbic <glink ref="acid">acid</glink>," or "preservatives."</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Potassium sulfate</name>
			<formula>K<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>7778-80-5</cas>
			<density>2.66</density>
			<mp>1342 K</mp>
			<bp>1962 K</bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>The principal use of potassium sulfate is as a fertilizer. The crude salt is also used occasionally in the manufacture of glass.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="020" type="4">
	<an>20</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Calcium</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Calcium carbonate</name>
			<formula>CaCO<sub>3</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density>2.83</density>
			<mp>1098 K</mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<classes>
				<class>I</class>
			</classes>		
			<notes>
				<ptxt>The main use of calcium carbonate is in the construction industry, either as a building material in its own right (e.g. marble) or limestone aggregate for roadbuilding or as an ingredient of cement or as the starting material for the preparation of builder's lime by burning in a kiln.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Calcium carbonate is widely used as an extender in paints, in particular matte emulsion paint where typically 30% by weight of the paint is either chalk or marble.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Calcium carbonate is also widely used as a filler in plastics. Some typical examples include around 15 to 20% loading of chalk in uPVC drain pipe, 5 to 15% loading of stearate coated chalk or marble in uPVC window profile. Fine ground calcium carbonate is an essential ingredient in the microporous film used in babies nappies and some building films as the pores are nucleated around the calcium carbonate particles during the manufacture of the film by biaxial stretching.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Calcium carbonate is widely used medicinally as an inexpensive dietary calcium supplement(1), antacid, and/or phosphate binder. It is also used in the pharmaceutical industry as a base material for tablets of other pharmaceuticals.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>As a food additive, it is used in some soy milk products as a source of dietary calcium.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Calcium chloride</name>
			<formula>CaCl<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density>2.83</density>
			<mp>1045 K</mp>
			<bp>1873 K</bp>
			<classes>
				<class>I</class>
			</classes>		
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Because it is strongly hygroscopic, it can be used to dry air as well as other gases and organic liquids. In this capacity, it is known as a drying agent or desiccant.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Aided by the intense heat evolved during its dissolution, calcium chloride is also used as an ice-melting compound. Unlike the more-common sodium chloride (rock salt or halite), it is relatively harmless to plants and soil. It is also more effective at lower temperatures than sodium chloride.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Calcium chloride tastes extremely salty and is used an ingredient in some foods, especially pickles, to give a salty taste while not increasing the food's sodium content.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Calcium hypochlorite</name>
			<formula>Ca(ClO)<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Used for the disinfection of drinking water or swimming pool water. For use in outdoor swimming pools, calcium hypochlorite can be used as a sanitiser in combination with a cyanuric <glink ref="acid">acid</glink> stabiliser. The stabiliser will reduce the loss of chlorine because of UV radiation.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Calcium hypochlorite (known as 'bleaching powder') is also used for bleaching cotton and linen and used in the manufacture of chloroform.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Calcium oxide</name>
			<formula>CaO</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density>3.350</density>
			<mp>2845 K</mp>
			<bp>3123 K</bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Used in water and sewage treatment to reduce acidity, to soften, as a flocculant, and to remove phosphates and other impurities; in paper making to dissolve lignin, as a coagulant, and in bleaching; in agriculture to improve acidic soils; and in pollution control - in gas scrubbers to desulfurize waste gases and to treat many liquid effluents. It has traditionally been used in the burial of bodies in open graves, to hide the smell of decomposition.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Hydroxylapatite</name>
			<formula>Ca<sup>5</sup>(PO<sup>4</sup>)<sup>3</sup>(OH)</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density>3.156</density>
			<mp>2845 K</mp>
			<bp>3123 K</bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Hydroxylapatite makes up 70% of bone, carbonated-calcium deficient hydroxylapatite is the main mineral of which dental enamel and dentin are comprised.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Lime sulfur</name>
			<formula></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Lime sulfur is sold as a spray for deciduous trees to control fungi, bacteria and insects living or dormant on the surface of the bark. Lime sulfur burns leaves so it is not as useful for evergreen plants.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Bonsai enthusiasts use undiluted lime sulfur to bleach and sterilise portions of trees to give an aged look known as Jin.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="021" type="2">
	<an>21</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Scandium</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Scandium(III) chloride</name>
			<formula>ScCl<sub>3</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density>2.39</density>
			<mp>1233 K</mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<classes>
				<class>I</class>
			</classes>		
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Is found in halide lamps, optical fibers, electronic ceramics, and lasers.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="022" type="2">
	<an>22</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Titanium</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Titanium boride</name>
			<formula>TiB<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>12045-63-5</cas>
			<density>4.52</density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>An extremely hard ceramic material with excellent corrosion resistance at high temperatures and very good wear resistance which does not occur naturally in earth. Many TiB2 applications are inhibited by economic factors, particularly the costs of densifying a high melting point material. Current use of this material appears to be limited to specialized applications in such areas as impact resistant armour, cutting tools, crucibles and wear resistant coatings.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Titanium carbide</name>
			<formula>TiC</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>12070-08-05</cas>
			<density>5.1</density>
			<mp>3443 K</mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>An extremely hard <glink ref="refractory">refractory</glink> ceramic material, similar to tungsten carbide. It is commercially used in tool bits cutting tools. It is mainly used in preparation of cermets, which are frequently used to machine steel materials at high cutting speed.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Tool bits without tungsten content can be made of titanium carbide in nickel-cobalt matrix cermet, enhancing the cutting speed and precision and smoothness of the workpiece. This material is sometimes called high-tech ceramics and is used as a heat shield for atmospheric re-entry of space shuttles and similar vehicles. The substance may be also polished and used in scratch-proof watches.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Titanium dioxide</name>
			<formula>TiO<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>12070-08-05</cas>
			<density>5.1</density>
			<mp>3443 K</mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Titanium dioxide is the most widely used white pigment because of its brightness and very high refractive index, in which it is surpassed only by a few other materials. When deposited as a thin film, its refractive index and colour make it an excellent reflective optical coating for dielectric mirrors. TiO2 is also an effective opacifier in powder form, where it is employed as a pigment to provide whiteness and opacity to products such as paints, coatings, plastics, papers, inks, foods, and most toothpastes. In cosmetic and skin care products, titanium dioxide is used both as a pigment and a thickener, and in almost every sunblock with a physical blocker, titanium dioxide is found both because of its refractive index and its resistance to discolouration under ultraviolet light. This advantage enhances its stability and ability to protect the skin from ultraviolet light. Titanium dioxide is used as a white food dye. In that use, its E number is E171.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Titanium nitride</name>
			<formula>TiN</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp>3203 K</mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>An extremely hard ceramic material, often used as a coating on titanium <glink ref="alloy">alloy</glink>, steel, carbide, and <elink ref="13">aluminium</elink> components to improve the substrate's surface properties. Far and away the most common use for TiN coating is for edge retention and corrosion resistance on machine tooling, such as drill bits and milling cutters, often improving their lifetime by a factor of three or more.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Because of its metallic gold colour, it is used to coat costume jewellery and automotive trim for decorative purposes. TiN is also widely used as a top-layer coating, usually with <elink ref="28">nickel</elink> or <elink ref="24">chromium</elink> plated substrates, on consumer plumbing fixtures and door hardware.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="023" type="2">
	<an>23</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Vanadium</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Vanadium carbide</name>
			<formula>VC</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>12070-10-9</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp>3153 K</mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>An extremely hard <glink ref="refractory">refractory</glink> ceramic material. It is commercially used in tool bits cutting tools. It has the appearance of gray metallic powder with cubic crystal structure. Vanadium carbide is chemically stable and has excellent high-temperature property. It can be used as an additive to tungsten carbide to fine the carbide crystals to improve the property of the cermet.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Vanadium(V) oxide</name>
			<formula>V<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>1314-62-1</cas>
			<density>3.357</density>
			<mp>963 K</mp>
			<bp>2020 K</bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>The most important compound of vanadium. Upon heating it can reversibly lose <elink ref="8">oxygen</elink> to the air. Related to this is its ability to catalyse the delivery of <elink ref="8">oxygen</elink> from the air to compounds such as sulfur dioxide, benzene and naphthalene, which is the basis for its industrial use as a catalyst in the manufacture of sulfuric <glink ref="acid">acid</glink>, maleic anhydride and phthalic anhydride, respectively. It is a poisonous orange solid which, because of its high oxidation state, is both an amphoteric oxide and an oxidising agent.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="024" type="2">
	<an>24</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Chromium</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Chromium carbide</name>
			<formula>Cr<sub>3</sub>C<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>12012-61-9</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>An extremely hard <glink ref="refractory">refractory</glink> ceramic material, is highly corrosion-resistant, and does not oxidize even at high temperature (1000-1100&degree;C). Chromium carbide is used as a thermal spray material for protecting the underlying metal surface, and as an additive to corrosion-resistant and wear-resistant materials. It is used in coatings of bearings, seals, orifices, and valve seals.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Chromium(IV) oxide</name>
			<formula>CrO<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>12018-01-8</cas>
			<density>4.9</density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>A synthetic magnetic substance once widely used in magnetic tape. With the increasing popularity of CDs and DVDs, the use of chromium(IV) oxide has declined. However, it is still used in data tape applications for enterprise-class storage systems. It is still considered today by many oxide and tape manufacturers to have been the most perfect magnetic recording particulate ever invented.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="025" type="2">
	<an>25</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Manganese</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Manganese(II) carbonate</name>
			<formula>MnCO<sub>3</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is widely used as an additive to plant fertilizers to cure manganese deficient crops. It is also used in many health foods. It is also used in ceramics as a glaze colourant and flux.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Manganese(IV) oxide</name>
			<formula>MnO<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>1313-13-9</cas>
			<density>5.026</density>
			<mp>808 K</mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>The principal use for MnO2 is for dry-cell batteries, such as the alkaline battery and the zinc-carbon battery.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="026" type="2">
	<an>26</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Iron</name>	
	<compounds>	
		<compound>
			<name>Haemoglobin</name>
			<formula>C<sub>2952</sub>H<sub>4664</sub>N<sub>812</sub>O<sub>832</sub>S<sub>8</sub>Fe<sub>4</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>The iron-containing oxygen-transport metalloprotein in the red cells of the blood in mammals and other animals. Hemoglobin in vertebrates transports oxygen from the lungs to the rest of the body, such as to the muscles, where it releases the oxygen load. Hemoglobin also has a variety of other gas-transport and effect-modulation duties, which vary from species to species, and which in invertebrates may be quite diverse.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Iron(II) sulfate</name>
			<formula>FeSO<sub>4</sub>.H<sub>2</sub>O</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>7720-78-7</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp>337 K</mp>
			<bp>363 K</bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>In horticulture it is used as a lawn conditioner and moss killer, traditionally referred to as sulphate of iron.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Ferrous sulfate is also used to treat iron-deficiency anemia. Side effects of therapy may include nausea and epigastric abdominal discomfort after taking iron. These side effects can be minimized by taking ferrous sulfate at bedtime.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Ferrous sulfate can also be used to colour concrete. It is best used for newly cured concrete. Mix with water until saturated and spray onto concrete. The colour will range from yellow to rust.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Iron(III) chloride</name>
			<formula>FeCl<sub>3</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>7705-08-0</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp>579 K</mp>
			<bp>588 K</bp>
			<classes>
				<class>HA</class>
				<class>T</class>
			</classes>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Most widely used for etching copper in the production of printed circuit boards.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Iron(III) chloride is also used as a catalyst for the reaction of ethylene with chlorine, forming ethylene dichloride (1,2-Dichloroethane), an important commodity chemical, which is mainly used for the industrial production of vinyl <elink ref="17">chloride</elink>, the monomer for making PVC.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>It is also commonly used by knife craftsmen and swordsmiths to stain blades, as to give a contrasting effect to the metal, and also to view metal layering or imperfections.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Iron(III) oxide</name>
			<formula>Fe<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>1309-37-1</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp>1838 K</mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Used in magnetic storage, for example in the magnetic layer of floppy disks.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>A very fine powder of ferric oxide is known as jeweller's rouge, red rouge, or simply rouge. It is used to put the final polish on metallic jewellery and lenses, and historically as a cosmetic.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="027" type="2">
	<an>27</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Cobalt</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Cerulean blue</name>
			<formula></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<densityl></densityl>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Cerulean blue is a cerulean (light blue or azure) pigment used in artistic painting. It is particularly valuable for painting atmospheric shades because of the purity of the blue (specifically the lack of greenish hues). The pigment is regarded as permanent: in oil, no other blue pigment retains colour as well.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>It was discovered in 1805 by Andreas Hopfner</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Cobalt green</name>
			<formula>CoO and ZnO</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<densityl></densityl>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Cobalt green (Rinmann's green), is a translucent green pigment made by mixing cobalt(II) oxide and zinc oxide and heating. It was invented by Swedish chemist Sven Rinmann in 1780. Although it is stable and can be safely mixed with other pigments, it is rarely used because it is a weak pigment for its cost.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Cobalt(II) chloride</name>
			<formula>CoCl<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>7646-79-9</cas>
			<density>3.356</density>
			<mp>1008K</mp>
			<bp>1322K</bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Because of the dramatic colour change from anhydrous to hydrous and the ease of the reaction, cobalt chloride is used as an indicator of water.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Anyhdrous cobalt chloride is light blue, hydrous cobalt chloride (CoCl<sub>2</sub>(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>6</sub>) is bright pink.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Cobalt(II) oxide</name>
			<formula>CoO</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>1307-96-6</cas>
			<density>6.1</density>
			<mp>2206 K</mp>
			<bp>? K</bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>A blackish gray powder used extensively in the ceramics industry (earliest examples go back to 12th century Germany) as an additive to create blue coloured (a deep shade called cobalt blue) glazes and enamels as well as in the chemical industry for producing cobaltous salts.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Cyanocobalamin (Vitamin B<sub>12</sub>)</name>
			<formula>C<sub>63</sub>H<sub>88</sub>CoN<sub>14</sub>O<sub>14</sub>P</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Vitamin B<sub>12</sub> is required by many organisms, including humans. Deficiency causes anemia.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Vitamin B<sub>12</sub> is naturally found in foods including meat (especially liver and shellfish), eggs, and milk products.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="028" type="2">
	<an>28</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Nickel</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Nickel(II) hydroxide</name>
			<formula>Ni(OH)<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Commonly used in the electrodes of rechargable batteries.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="029" type="2">
	<an>29</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Coppper</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Bismuth strontium calcium copper oxide</name>
			<formula>Bi<sub>2</sub>Sr<sub>2</sub>Ca<sub>n</sub>Cu<sub>n+1</sub>O<sub>2n+6</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>A family of high-temperature superconductors and also the first high-temperature superconductors to be discovered which did not contain a <glink ref="ree">rare earth element</glink>.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Copper gluconate</name>
			<formula>C<sub>12</sub>H<sub>22</sub>CuO<sub>14</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>814-91-5</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Dietary supplement -- metabolizable copper to treat copper deficiency. Used to treat acne vulgaris, common cold, hypertension, premature labor, Leishmaniasis, visceral postoperative complications.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Copper(II) arsenate</name>
			<formula>Cu<sub>3</sub>(AsO<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>.4H<sub>2</sub>O or Cu<su>5</su>H<sub>2</sub>(AsO<sub>4</sub>)<sub>4</sub>.2H<sub>2</sub>O</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>7778-41-8</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Is an insecticide used in agriculture, also used as a herbicide, fungicide, and a rodenticide.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Copper(II) bromide</name>
			<formula>CuBr<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>7789-45-9</cas>
			<density>4.71</density>
			<mp>771 K</mp>
			<bp>1173 K</bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is used in photographic processing as an intensifier and as a brominating agent in organic synthesis.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>It is also used in the copper vapour laser, a class of laser where the medium is copper bromide vapour formed in situ from <elink ref="1">hydrogen</elink> bromide in reaction with the enclosing copper discharge tube. [2] Producing yellow or green light, it is used in dermatological applications.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Copper indium gallium selenide (CIGS)</name>
			<formula>Cu(Ga,In)Se<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<densityl></densityl>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>					
			<notes>
				<ptxt>CIGS is a new semiconductor used mainly in photovoltaic cells (CIGS cells).</ptxt>
				<ptxt>CIGS solar cells are not as efficient as crystalline silicon solar cells, but they are expected to be substantially cheaper. CIGS can be printed directly onto molybdenum coated glass sheets. Solar cells made from crystalline silicon are made of slices of solid silicon and require therefore more expensive semiconductor material.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Copper(II) sulfate</name>
			<formula>CuSO<sub>4</sub>.5H<sub>2</sub>O</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>7758-99-8</cas>
			<density>2.284</density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It can be used to plate metals with copper, as a fungicide or herbicide, or as a chemical test for water (the anhydrous form will absorb water, turning blue).</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Copper sulfate is also used to test blood for anemia. A drop of the patient's blood is dropped into a container of copper sulfate, if it sinks within a certain time, then the patient has sufficient haemogloblin levels and is not anemic. If the blood floats or sinks too slowly, then the patient is iron-deficient and may be anemic.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Verdigris</name>
			<formula>Cu(CH<sub>3</sub>COO)<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It commonly occurs by the action of acetic <glink ref="acid">acid</glink> when copper, brass or bronze is weathered and exposed to air or seawater over a period of time. Its name comes from the Middle English vertegrez, from the Old French verte grez, an alteration of vert-de-Grice - verd (green), de (of), and Grice (Greece)- "green of Greece".</ptxt>
				<ptxt>The vivid green colour of verdigris makes it a very common pigment. Until the 19th century, verdigris was the most vibrant green pigment available and frequently used in painting. Verdigris is lightfast in oil paint, as numerous examples of 15th century paintings show. However, its lightfastness and air resistance is very low in other media. Copper resinate, made from verdigris, is not lightfast, even in oil paint. In the presence of light and air, green copper resinate becomes stable brown copper oxide.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Yttrium barium copper oxide</name>
			<formula></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt></ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="030" type="2">
	<an>30</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Zinc</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Cadmium zinc telluride</name>
			<formula>CdZnTe</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>A wide, direct bandgap semiconductor, it is used in a variety of applications, including radiation detectors, photorefractive gratings, electro-optic modulators and terahertz generation and detection. <elink ref="48">Cadmium</elink> zinc telluride is highly toxic to humans. It should not be ingested, nor its dust inhaled, and it should not be handled without appropriate gloves.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Mercury zinc telluride</name>
			<formula>HgZnTe</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Used in infrared detectors and arrays for infrared imaging and infrared astronomy.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Mercury zinc telluride has better chemical, thermal, and mechanical stability than <elink ref="80">mercury</elink> <elink ref="48">cadmium</elink> <elink ref="52">telluride</elink>. The bandgap of MZT is more sensitive to composition fluctuations than that of MCT, which may be an issue for reproducible device fabrication. MZT is less amenable than MCT to fabrication of complex heterostructures by molecular beam epitaxy.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Zinc acetate</name>
			<formula>Zn(CH<sub>3</sub>COO)<sub>2</sub>.(2H<sub>2</sub>O)</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is often used to treat zinc deficiencies, for instance Wilson's disease.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Industrial applications include wood preserving, manufacturing other zinc salts, polymer cross-linking, making ethylene acetate, and as a dye mordant and analytical <glink ref="reagent">reagent</glink>.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Zinc acetate is also found in the form of an ointment, a topical lotion. It is an anesthetic which can be used to treat minor pain.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Zinc antimonide</name>
			<formula>ZnSb</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>12039-35-9</cas>
			<density>6.33</density>
			<mp>838 K</mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is a semiconducting intermetallic compound. It is used in transistors, infrared detectors and thermal imagers, as well as magnetoresistive devices.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Zinc hydroxide</name>
			<formula>Zn(OH)<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>20427-58-1</cas>
			<density>3.053</density>
			<mp>398 K</mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>One major use as as an absorbant in surgical dressings.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Zinc phosphate</name>
			<formula>Zn<sub>3</sub>(PO<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>7779-90-9</cas>
			<density>4</density>
			<mp>1173 K</mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Used as a corrosion resistant coating on metal surfaces either as part of an electroplating process or applied as a primer.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Zinc selenide</name>
			<formula>ZnSe</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>1315-09-9</cas>
			<density>5.27</density>
			<mp>1798 K</mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Used to form light-emitting diodes and diode lasers. It emits blue light.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Zinc stearate</name>
			<formula>Zn(C<sub>15</sub>H<sub>35</sub>O<sub>2</sub>)<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>557-05-1</cas>
			<density>1.095</density>
			<mp>~423 K</mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Zinc Stearate is a zinc soap that repels water, insoluble in alcohol, ether, soluble in benzene. It is the most powerful mold release agent among all metal soaps. It contains no electrolyte and has hydrophobic effect. Its main application areas are the plastics and rubber industry where they are used as releasing agents and lubricants which can be easily incorporated.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Zinc Stearate is also the chief ingredient in fanning powder, used by magicians and card manipulators to decrease the friction between the cards. This gives the card a smoothe, and "floating" feeling as the cards are spread for fans and/or flourishes.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Zinc sulfate</name>
			<formula>ZnSO<sub>4</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is used to supply zinc in animal feeds, fertilizers, and agricultural sprays.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>ZnSO<sub>4</sub>.7H<sub>2</sub>O is used in making lithopone, in coagulation baths for rayon, in electrolytes for zinc plating, as a mordant in dyeing, as a preservative for skins and leather and in medicine as an astringent and emetic.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>An aqueous solution of zinc sulfate is claimed to be effective at removing moss from roofs. Spraying a mixture on moss will allow the wind to simply blow off the remaining debris, however it is not recommended for use on lawns as it is as effective at removing grass as it is moss.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="031" type="5">
	<an>31</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Gallium</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Gallium Arsenide</name>
			<formula>GaAs</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>1303-00-0</cas>
			<density>5.3176</density>
			<mp>1511 K</mp>
			<bp>? K</bp>
			<classes>
				<class>C</class>
				<class>HT</class>
			</classes>		
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is an important semiconductor and is used to make devices such as microwave frequency integrated circuits, infrared LEDs, laser diodes and solar cells.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>GeAs has some electronic properties which are superior to <elink ref="14">silicon's</elink>, these allow it to function at frequencies greater than 250GHz, and generate less noise than <elink ref="14">silicon</elink> devices when operated at higher frequencies. GeAs is also capable of emitting light, <elink ref="14">silicon</elink> is very poor at emitting light.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="032" type="0">
	<an>32</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Germanium</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Silicon-germanium</name>
			<formula>SiGe</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>63148-62-9</cas>
			<density>0.965</density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>This semiconductor material is commonly used in the integrated circuit manufacturing industry.</ptxt>				
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Germanium dioxide (germania)</name>
			<formula>GeO<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>1310-53-8</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp>1388 K</mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Germanium dioxide's refractive index and optical dispersion properties make it useful as an optical material for wide-angle lenses and in optical microscope objective lenses. It is transparent in infrared.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Mixture of <elink ref="14">silicon</elink> dioxide and <elink ref="32">germanium</elink> dioxide ("silica-germania") is used as an optical material for optical fibres and optical waveguides. Controlling the ratio of the elements allows precise control of refractive index. Silica-germania glasses have lower viscosity and higher refractive index than pure silica.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="033" type="0">
	<an>33</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="y">Arsenic</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Arsenic acid</name>
			<formula>H<sub>3</sub>AsO<sub>4</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>7778-39-4</cas>
			<density>2</density>
			<mp>308.65 K</mp>
			<bp>433.15 K</bp>
			<classes>
				<class>HT</class>
			</classes>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Arsenic <glink ref="acid">acid</glink> is used in wood treatment, finishing agent for glass and metal, in the manufacturing of dyestuffs and organic arsenic compounds and also in soil sterilant. It can also be used as a herbicide, insecticide or rodenticide.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Arsenic trioxide</name>
			<formula>Ar<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>1327-53-3</cas>
			<density>3.86</density>
			<mp>547 K</mp>
			<bp>733 K</bp>
			<classes>
				<class>HT</class>
			</classes>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Starting point for the manufacture of arsenic-based pesticides and the manufacture of certain arsenic-based pharamaceuticals and vetinary products.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>It is used as a decolourizing agent for glasses and enamels and as a preservative for wood.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Arsenic trioxide is also used to treat leukemia in patients who have not responded to other medications.</ptxt>	
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Gallium Arsenide</name>
			<formula>GaAs</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>1303-00-0</cas>
			<density>5.3176</density>
			<mp>1511 K</mp>
			<bp>? K</bp>
			<classes>
				<class>C</class>
				<class>HT</class>
			</classes>		
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is an important semiconductor and is used to make devices such as microwave frequency integrated circuits, infrared LEDs, laser diodes and solar cells.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>GeAs has some electronic properties which are superior to <elink ref="14">silicon's</elink>, these allow it to function at frequencies greater than 250GHz, and generate less noise than <elink ref="14">silicon</elink> devices when operated at higher frequencies. GeAs is also capable of emitting light, <elink ref="14">silicon</elink> is very poor at emitting light.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="034" type="3">
	<an>34</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="y">Selenium</name>	
	<header>
		<ptxt>Very few compounds of selenium have any important practical applications.</ptxt>
	</header>
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Copper indium gallium selenide (CIGS)</name>
			<formula>Cu(Ga,In)Se<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<densityl></densityl>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>					
			<notes>
				<ptxt>CIGS is a new semiconductor used mainly in photovoltaic cells (CIGS cells).</ptxt>
				<ptxt>CIGS solar cells are not as efficient as crystalline silicon solar cells, but they are expected to be substantially cheaper. CIGS can be printed directly onto molybdenum coated glass sheets. Solar cells made from crystalline silicon are made of slices of solid silicon and require therefore more expensive semiconductor material.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Lead(II) selenide</name>
			<formula>PbSe</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<densityl></densityl>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>					
			<notes>
				<ptxt>A semiconductor used in the manufacture of infrared detectors for thermal imaging.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>		
		<compound>
			<name>Selenium Sulfide</name>
			<formula>SeS<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<densityl></densityl>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>					
			<notes>
				<ptxt>This compound is used to treat seborrhea, or "oily skin." It is sometimes added to shampoos for people with especially oily hair.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Selenium Diethyldithiocarbonate</name>
			<formula>Se[SC(S)N(C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>5</sub>)<sub>2</sub>]<sub>4</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<densityl></densityl>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>					
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Used as a vulcanizing, "toughening", agent for rubber products.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Zinc selenide</name>
			<formula>ZnSe</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>1315-09-9</cas>
			<density>5.27</density>
			<mp>1798 K</mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>A semiconductor material used to form blue light-emitting diodes and diode lasers.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="035" type="6">
	<an>35</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Bromine</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Ammonium bromide</name>
			<formula>NH<sub>4</sub>Br</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Used in manufacturing photographic chemicals and emulsion. It is also used as a flame retardant.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Lithium bromide</name>
			<formula>LiBr</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>7550-35-8</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp>825 K</mp>
			<bp>1538 K</bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>An extremely <glink ref="hygroscopic">hygroscopic</glink> and oftern used as a <glink ref="desiccant">dessicant</glink>. Along with lithium chloride (LiCl), it is frequently used in air conditioning and industrial drying systems.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="036" type="7">
	<an>36</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Krypton</name>
	<header>
		<ptxt>Like the other noble gases, krypton is chemically inert. However, following the first successful synthesis of <elink ref="54">xenon</elink> compounds in 1962, synthesis of krypton difluoride was reported in 1963. Other fluorides and a salt of a krypton oxoacid have also been found. ArKr<sup>+</sup> and KrH<sup>+</sup> molecule-ions have been investigated and there is evidence for KrXe or KrXe<sup>+</sup>. At the University of Helsinki in Finland, HKrCN and HKrCCH (krypton hydride-cyanide and hydrokryptoacetylene) were synthesized and determined to be stable up to 40K.</ptxt>
		<ptxt>No useful or commercial compounds of krypton exist at this time.</ptxt>
	</header>
</element>

<element media="y" index="037" type="1">
	<an>37</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Rubidium</name>
	<header>
		<ptxt>Several rubidium compounds are known, with the exception of rubidium telluride (Rb<sub>2</sub>Te which has found some use in UV detectors in space) these compounds have little or no commercial or industrial value.</ptxt>
	</header>
</element>

<element media="y" index="038" type="4">
	<an>38</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Strontium</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Bismuth strontium calcium copper oxide</name>
			<formula>Bi<sub>2</sub>Sr<sub>2</sub>Ca<sub>n</sub>Cu<sub>n+1</sub>O<sub>2n+6</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>A family of high-temperature superconductors and also the first high-temperature superconductors to be discovered which did not contain a <glink ref="ree">rare earth element</glink>.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Strontium aluminate</name>
			<formula>SrAlO<sub>3</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>12004-37-4</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>When activated with a suitable dopant (eg. <elink ref="63">europium</elink>, then it is labeled SrAlO<sub>3</sub>:Eu), it acts as a photoluminescent phosphor with long persistence of phosphorescence. The glow intensity depends on the particle size; generally, the bigger the particles, the better the glow.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Strontium aluminate is vastly superior phosphor than its predecessor, copper-activated zinc sulfide; it is about 10 times brighter, 10 times longer glowing, and 10 times more expensive than ZnS:Cu. It is frequently used in glow in the dark toys, where it displaces the cheaper but less efficient ZnS:Cu.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Strontium nitrate</name>
			<formula>Sr(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>10042-76-9</cas>
			<density>2.986</density>
			<mp>43 K</mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is an oxidizer and imparts a deep red colour to flames. It has found use in flares and pyrotechnic compositions including stars and rocket propellants. Woodchips soaked in a strong solution of strontium nitrate and then thoroughly dried, will burn with a deep red.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Strontium ranelate</name>
			<formula>C<sub>12</sub>H<sub>6</sub>N<sub>2</sub>O<sub>8</sub>SSr<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>135459-90-4</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is used as a medication for osteoporosis.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="039" type="2">
	<an>39</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Yttrium</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Yttrium aluminium garnet</name>
			<formula>Y<sub>3</sub>Al<sub>5</sub>O<sub>12</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>A synthetic crystalline material of the garnet group, used as the active laser medium in various solid-state lasers..</ptxt>
				<ptxt>It also finds use in jewellery as a <elink ref="6">diamond</elink> simulant. Coloured variants are faceted and valued (as synthetics) for their clarity, durability, high refractive index and dispersion.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Yttrium(III) oxide</name>
			<formula>Y<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>1314-36-9</cas>
			<density>5.010</density>
			<mp>2963 K</mp>
			<bp>4573 K</bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is the most important yttrium compound and is widely used to make YVO<sub>4</sub>:Eu and Y<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>:Eu phosphors that give the red colour in colour TV picture tubes. Yttrium oxide is also used to make yttrium-iron-garnets, which are very effective microwave filters.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="040" type="2">
	<an>40</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Zirconium</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Zirconium carbide</name>
			<formula>ZrC</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>12020-14-3</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp>3805 K</mp>
			<bp>5373 K</bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>An extremely hard <glink ref="refractory">refractory</glink> ceramic material, commercially used in tool bits for cutting tools. It is usually processed by sintering. It has the appearance of a gray metallic powder with cubic crystal structure. It is highly corrosion resistant. Zirconium carbide reacts with water and acids and is <glink ref="pyrophoric">pyrophoric</glink>.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Hafnium-free zirconium <elink ref="6">carbide</elink> and <elink ref="41">niobium</elink> <elink ref="6">carbide</elink> can be used as <glink ref="refractory">refractory</glink> coatings in nuclear reactors. It is also used as an abrasive, in metal cladding, in cermets, incandescent filaments and cutting tools.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Zirconium dioxide</name>
			<formula>ZrO<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>1314-23-4</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp>2988 K</mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Sometimes known as zirconia, is a white crystalline oxide of zirconium. Its most naturally occurring form, with a monoclinic crystalline structure, is the rare mineral, baddeleyite. The high temperature cubic crystalline form, called 'cubic zirconia', is rarely, if ever, found in nature, but is synthesized in various colours for use as a gemstone and is the best-known diamond simulant.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Zirconium dioxide is one of the most studied ceramic materials. Pure ZrO<sub>2</sub> has a monoclinic crystal structure at room temperature and transitions to tetragonal and cubic at increasing temperatures.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>It is used as a <glink ref="refractory">refractory</glink> material, in insulation, abrasives, enamels and glazes. Stabilized zirconia is used in <elink ref="8">oxygen</elink> sensors and fuel cell membranes because it has a unique ability to allow oxygen ions to move freely through the crystal structure at high temperatures. This high ionic conductivity (and a low electronic conductivity) makes it one of the most useful electroceramics.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Zirconia is one of few compounds that actually becomes conductive at high temperatures, and more conductive, as its temperature increases. Zirconia starts out with a very high resistance at room temperature, greater than 1 trillion ohm-cm. As the temperature increases it has less than 20,000 ohm-cm at 500 degrees Celsius, to having less than 1,000 ohm-cm of resistance at 1,000 degrees Celsius. It loses nearly all of its resistance around 2,000 degrees Celsius, and becomes a very good conductor.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Zirconium(IV) hydroxide</name>
			<formula>Zr(OH)<sub>4</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>14475-63-9</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp>823 K</mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Zirconium hydroxide is primarily used as in intermediate for the manufacture of zirconium compounds. It is used in pigments, glass and dyes.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Zirconium nitride</name>
			<formula>ZrN</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>25658-42-8</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp>3233 K</mp>
			<bp></bp>					
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is hard and <glink ref="refractory">refractory</glink>. It has been used recently as an alternative to <elink ref="22">titanium</elink> nitride for coating drill bits. Both coatings are supposed to keep the bit sharper and cooler during cutting. It is also used in refractories, cermets and laboratory cruibles.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="041" type="2">
	<an>41</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Niobium</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Niobium carbide</name>
			<formula>NbC and Nb<sub>2</sub>C</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>12069-94-2</cas>
			<density>7.820</density>
			<mp>3763 K</mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>An extremely hard <glink ref="refractory">refractory</glink> ceramic material, commercially used in tool bits for cutting tools. <elink ref="40">Zirconium</elink> carbide and niobium carbide can be used as <glink ref="refractory">refractory</glink> coatings in nuclear reactors.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Niobium-tin</name>
			<formula>Nb<sub>3</sub>Sn</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Used industrially as a type II superconductor. Its critical temperature is 18.3 kelvins. It is usually used at 4.2 K, the <glink ref="bp">boiling point</glink> of liquid <elink ref="2">helium</elink>.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="042" type="2">
	<an>42</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Molybdenum</name>
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Molybdenum disulfide</name>
			<formula>MoS<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>1317-33-5</cas>
			<density>5.06</density>
			<mp>1458 K</mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>The structure, appearance, and feel of molybdenum disulfide is similar to <elink ref="6">graphite</elink> - a sandwich of layers of molybdenum atoms between the layers of sulfur atoms.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Finely powdered MoS<sub>2</sub> with particle sizes in the range of 1-100 um is a common dry lubricant. It is also often mixed into various oils and greases, which allows the mechanisms lubricated by it to keep running for a while longer, even in cases of almost complete oil loss - finding an important use in aircraft engines. It is also used as a lubricating additive to special plastics, notably nylon and teflon.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Another application is for coating bullets, giving them easier passage through the rifle barrel with less deformation and better ballistic accuracy.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="043" type="2">
	<an>43</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Technetium</name>
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Sodium pertechnetate</name>
			<formula>NaTcO<sub>4</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>A gamma-emitting radionuclide imaging agent used for the diagnosis of diseases in many tissues, particularly in the gastrointestinal system, cardiovascular and cerebral circulation, brain, thyroid, and joints.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="044" type="2">
	<an>44</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Ruthenium</name>
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Ruthenium red</name>
			<formula>[(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>5</sub>Ru-O-Ru(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>4</sub>-O-Ru(NH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>5</sub>]<sup>6+</sup></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>A biological stain used to visualize polyanionic areas of membranes.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="045" type="2">
	<an>45</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Rhodium</name>
	<header>
		<ptxt>Many rhodium compounds are known but these compounds have little or no commercial or industrial value.</ptxt>
	</header>
</element>

<element media="y" index="046" type="2">
	<an>46</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Palladium</name>
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Palladium(II) acetate</name>
			<formula>C<sub>4</sub>H<sub>6</sub>O<sub>4</sub>Pd</formula>
			<mass>224.50</mass>
			<cas>3375-31-3</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Palladium acetate is a catalyst for many organic reactions by combining with many common classes of organic compounds such as alkenes, dienes, and alkyl, aryl, and vinyl halides to form reactive adducts.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Palladium(II) chloride</name>
			<formula>PdCl<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass>177.33</mass>
			<cas>7647-10-1</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Palladium(II) chloride is a common starting point in the synthesis of other palladium compounds.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Even when dry, palladium(II) chloride is able to rapidly stain stainless steel. Thus, palladium(II) chloride solutions are sometimes used to test for the corrosion-resistance of stainless steel. Palladium(II) chloride is sometimes used in <elink ref="6">carbon</elink> monoxide detectors.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="047" type="2">
	<an>47</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Silver</name>
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Silver chloride</name>
			<formula>AgCl</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density>5.06</density>
			<mp>728 K</mp>
			<bp>1823 K</bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Used in the manufacture of photographic film since it turns darker when exposed to light. It is also used in Photochromic Lenses.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Silver chloride's low solubility makes it a useful addition to pottery glazes for the production of "Inglaze lustre".</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Silver chloride has the ability to eliminate or flush out <elink ref="80">mercury</elink> from the body.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Silver cyanide</name>
			<formula>AgCN</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>506-64-9</cas>
			<density>3.95</density>
			<mp>593 K</mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<classes>
				<class>HT</class>
			</classes>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is largely stable, primarily used in silver plating; however exposure to air or moisture can result in the release of poisonous <elink ref="1">hydrogen</elink> cyanide gas. Violent explosions can occur if it is mixed with <elink ref="9">fluorine</elink> or melted with nitrite salts.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Silver nitrate</name>
			<formula>AgNO<sub>3</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>7761-88-8</cas>
			<density>4.35</density>
			<mp>485 K</mp>
			<bp>717 K</bp>
			<classes>
				<class>HA</class>
				<class>T</class>
			</classes>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>A light-sensitive ingredient in photographic film.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Photons from sunlight, X-rays or other sources, initiate a chemical chain reaction: when photons strike silver nitrate <glink ref="molecule">molecules</glink>, they free electrons from the silver <glink ref="ion">ions</glink>. These free <glink ref="electron">electrons</glink> roam through the crystal and settle in structural imperfections called sensitivity specks. These specks attract positive silver <glink ref="ion">ions</glink>, which are then neutralized to form groups of stable silver <glink ref="atom">atoms</glink>, creating a latent image that is chemically developed to reveal a photographic image.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Silver sulfadiazine</name>
			<formula></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>A topical antibacterial used primarily on second- and third-degree burns. The cream is kept applied to the burned skin at all times, for the duration of the healing period or until a graft is applied. It prevents the growth of a wide array of bacteria, as well as yeast, on the damaged skin. Silver sulfadiazine is typically delivered in a 1% solution suspended in a water-soluble base. The chemical itself is poorly soluble, and has only very limited penetration through the skin. Only when applied to very large area burns is absorption into the body generally a problem.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="048" type="2">
	<an>48</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Cadmium</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Cadmium sulfide</name>
			<formula>CdS</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>1306-23-6</cas>
			<density>4.82</density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Synthetic <elink ref="48">cadmium</elink> pigments based on <elink ref="48">cadmium</elink> sulfide are valued for their good thermal stability in many polymers, for example in engineering plastics. By adding selenium in its formula its possible to obtain colours ranging from a greenish yellow to red violet pigment.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>It has useful properties for optoelectronics, being used in both photosensitive and photovoltaic devices. One simple use is as a photoresistor whose electrical resistance changes with incident light levels. Mixed with zinc sulfide, <elink ref="48">cadmium</elink> sulfide acts as a phosphor with long afterglow.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Cadmium zinc telluride</name>
			<formula>CdZnTe</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>A wide, direct bandgap semiconductor, it is used in a variety of applications, including radiation detectors, photorefractive gratings, electro-optic modulators and terahertz generation and detection. <elink ref="48">Cadmium</elink> <elik ref="30">zinc</elik> <elink ref="52">telluride</elink> is highly toxic to humans. It should not be ingested, nor its dust inhaled, and it should not be handled without appropriate gloves.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>		

<element media="y" index="049" type="5">
	<an>49</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Indium</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Aluminium gallium indium phosphide</name>
			<formula>AlGaInP</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>A semiconductor material used in the manufacture of light-emitting diodes of high-brightness red, orange, green, and yellow colour, to form the heterostructure emitting light. It is also used to make diode lasers.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Copper indium gallium selenide (CIGS)</name>
			<formula>Cu(Ga,In)Se<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<densityl></densityl>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>					
			<notes>
				<ptxt>CIGS is a new semiconductor used mainly in photovoltaic cells (CIGS cells).</ptxt>
				<ptxt>CIGS solar cells are not as efficient as crystalline silicon solar cells, but they are expected to be substantially cheaper. CIGS can be printed directly onto molybdenum coated glass sheets. Solar cells made from crystalline silicon are made of slices of solid silicon and require therefore more expensive semiconductor material.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Indium(III) arsenide</name>
			<formula>InAs</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>1303-11-3</cas>
			<density>5.680</density>
			<mp>1215 K</mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Used for construction of infrared detectors and diode lasers.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Indium(III) antimonide</name>
			<formula>InSb</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>1312-41-0</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>A narrow gap semiconductor material used in infrared detectors, including thermal imaging cameras, FLIR (forward looking infra-red) systems, infrared homing missile guidance systems, and in infrared astronomy.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Indium tin oxide</name>
			<formula>mixture of In<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> and SnO<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>1312-41-0</cas>
			<density>7.120</density>
			<mp>1800-2200 K</mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Mainly used to make transparent conductive coatings for liquid crystal displays, flat panel displays, plasma displays, touch panels, electronic ink applications, organic light-emitting diodes, and solar cells, and antistatic coatings and EMI shieldings.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>ITO is also used for various optical coatings, most notably infrared-reflecting coatings (hot mirrors) for architectural, automotive, and <elink ref="11">sodium</elink> vapour lamp glasses.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="050" type="5">
	<an>50</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="y">Tin</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Tin(II) chloride</name>
			<formula>SnCl<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>7772-99-8</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp>519 K</mp>
			<bp>896 K</bp>
			<classes>
				<class>A</class>
			</classes>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>A solution of tin(II) chloride containing a little hydrochloric <glink ref="acid">acid</glink> is used for the tin-plating of steel, in order to make tin cans. An electric potential is applied, and tin metal is formed at the cathode via electrolysis.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Stannous chloride is also added as a food additive with E number E512 to some canned and bottled foods, where it serves as a colour-retention agent and antioxidant.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Tin(IV) chloride</name>
			<formula>SnCl<sub>4</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>7646-78-8</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp>240 K</mp>
			<bp>387.1 K</bp>
			<classes>
				<class>A</class>
			</classes>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Stannic chloride was used as a chemical weapon in World War I. It is also used in the glass container industry for making an external coating containing tin(IV) oxide which toughens the glass.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Tin(IV) dioxide</name>
			<formula>SnO<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>18282-10-5</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp>1127K</mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>SnO<sub>2</sub> has been used as pigment in the manufacture of glasses, enamels and ceramic glazes. On its own SnO<sub>2</sub> gives a milky white colour; other colours are achieved when mixed with other metallic oxides e.g. V<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> yellow; Cr<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> pink; and Sb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> grey blue.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>SnO<sub>2</sub> is used in sensors of combustible gases. In these the sensor area is heated to a constant temperature (low 100s &degree;C) and in the presence of a combustible gas the electrical resistivity drops.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>		
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="051" type="0">
	<an>51</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Antimony</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Antimony pentoxide</name>
			<formula>Sb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>1314-60-9</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp>653 K</mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is used in a variety of industrial processes. It finds use as a flame retardant in ABS and other plastics, a flocculant in the production of <elink ref="22">titanium</elink> dioxide and is sometimes used in the production of glass, paint and adhesives.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Antimony trifluoride</name>
			<formula>SbF<sub>3</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>7783-56-4</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp>565 K</mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<classes>
				<class>HA</class>
			</classes>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>A light grey crystalline material often used in dyeing and pottery.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Antimony trioxide</name>
			<formula>Sb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>1309-64-4</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp>929 K</mp>
			<bp>1698 K</bp>
			<classes>
				<class>HA</class>
			</classes>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Antimony trioxide is the most important commercial compound of antimony. It is used as a flame retardant for textiles and polymers, an opacifying agent for glasses, ceramics and enamels and as a pigment.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="052" type="0">
	<an>52</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Tellurium</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Bismuth telluride</name>
			<formula>Bi<sub>2</sub>Te<sub>3</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>1304-82-1</cas>
			<density>7.7</density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<classes>
				<class>T</class>
			</classes>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is a semiconductor which is an efficient thermoelectric material for refrigeration or portable power generation.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>	
</element>

<element media="y" index="053" type="6">
	<an>53</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Iodine</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Ammonium iodide</name>
			<formula>NH<sub>4</sub>I</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>12027-06-4</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is used in photographic chemicals and some medications.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Iodic acid</name>
			<formula>HIO<sub>3</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>7782-68-5</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Iodic <glink ref="acid">acid</glink> is used as a standard strong <glink ref="acid">acid</glink> in analytical chemistry. It may be used to standardize solutions of both weak and strong bases, with methyl red or methyl orange as the indicator.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Lead(II) iodide</name>
			<formula>PbI<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>10101-63-0</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<classes>
				<class>T</class>
			</classes>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>As toxic, yellowish solid. In its crystalline form it is used as a detector material for high energy photons including x-rays and gamma rays.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Lithium iodide</name>
			<formula>LiI</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>10377-51-2</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Lithium <elink ref="53">iodide</elink> is used as an electrolyte for high temperature batteries. It is also used for long life batteries as required, for example, by cardiac pacemakers. The solid is used as a phosphor for neutron detection.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Nitrogen triiodide</name>
			<formula>NI<sub>3</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>13444-85-4</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Also called <elink ref="7">nitrogen</elink> <elink ref="53">iodide</elink>, is a highly explosive compound of <elink ref="7">nitrogen</elink> and iodine. It is a contact explosive, and small quantities explode with a gunpowder-like snap when touched by even a feather, releasing a volatile cloud of iodine vapour.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Small amounts of <elink ref="7">nitrogen</elink> triiodide are sometimes synthesized as a demonstration to chemistry students. However, because the compound is so unstable, it has not been used in blasting caps or primers for explosives.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>The reason for it's instability is due to the size difference between the two different types of <glink ref="atom">atoms</glink>. The three iodine atoms are much bigger than the <elink ref="7">nitrogen</elink> atom holding them together. Because of this, not only is the bond between <glink ref="nucleus">nuclei</glink> under much stress and therefore weaker, but the outside <glink ref="electron">electrons</glink> of the different iodine atoms are very close, which increases the overall instability of the <glink ref="molecule">molecule</glink>.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Potassium iodide</name>
			<formula>KI</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>7681-11-0</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp>953 K</mp>
			<bp>1600 K</bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Potassium <elink ref="53">iodide</elink> is used in photography, in the preparation of <elink ref="47">silver(I)</elink> <elink ref="53">iodide</elink> for high speed photographic film.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Potassium <elink ref="53">iodide</elink> may also be used to protect the thyroid from radioactive <elink ref="53">iodide</elink> in the event of an accident or terrorist attack at a nuclear power plant, or other nuclear attack, especially where a nuclear reactor is breached and the volatile radionuclides, which contain significant amount of <sup>131</sup>I, are released into the environment. Radioiodine is a particularly dangerous radionuclide because the body concentrates it in the thyroid gland.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Sodium iodide</name>
			<formula>NaI</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>7681-82-5</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp>933 K</mp>
			<bp>1577 K</bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Sodium <elink ref="53">iodide</elink> is commonly used to treat and prevent iodine deficiency. Solid crystals can be used to detect radiation (e.g. radiation from <elink ref="92">uranium</elink>) - a solid crystal of <elink ref="11">sodium</elink> <elink ref="53">iodide</elink> creates a pulse of light when radiation interacts with it.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Thyroxine (T<sub>4</sub>)</name>
			<formula>3,5,3',5'-tetra-iodothyronine</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<densityl></densityl>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>An important hormone produced by the thyroid gland.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>The thyroid hormones are essential to proper development and differentiation of all cells of the human body. These hormones also regulate protein, fat, and carbohydrate metabolism, affecting how human cells use energetic compounds. Numerous physiological and pathological stimuli influence thyroid hormone synthesis.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Hypothyroidism is a disorder where there is a deficiency of thyroxine. Thyrotoxicosis or hyperthyroidism is the clinical syndrome caused by an excess of circulating free thyroxine, free triiodothyronine, or both.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Triiodothyronine (T<sub>3</sub>)</name>
			<formula></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<densityl></densityl>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>An important hormone produced by the thyroid gland.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>The thyroid hormones are essential to proper development and differentiation of all cells of the human body. These hormones also regulate protein, fat, and carbohydrate metabolism, affecting how human cells use energetic compounds. Numerous physiological and pathological stimuli influence thyroid hormone synthesis.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Hypothyroidism is a disorder where there is a deficiency of thyroxine. Thyrotoxicosis or hyperthyroidism is the clinical syndrome caused by an excess of circulating free thyroxine, free triiodothyronine, or both.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>	
</element>

<element media="y" index="054" type="7">
	<an>54</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Xenon</name>
	<header>
		<ptxt>The first chemical compound of xenon, xenon hexafluoroplatinate, was synthesized in 1962. Now, many compounds of xenon are known, including xenon difluoride, xenon tetrafluoride, xenon hexafluoride, xenon tetroxide, xenon hydrate, xenon deuterate, and sodium perxenate. A highly explosive compound xenon trioxide has also been made.</ptxt>
		<ptxt>Recently at the University of Helsinki in Finland, a group of scientists prepared HXeH, HXeOH, and HXeCCH (xenon dihydride, xenon hydride-hydroxide, and hydroxenoacetylene). They are stable up to 40K.</ptxt>
		<ptxt>No useful or commercial compounds of xenon exist at this time.</ptxt>
	</header>
</element>

<element media="y" index="055" type="1">
	<an>55</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Caesium</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Caesium chloride</name>
			<formula>CsCl</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>7647-17-8</cas>
			<density>3.99 </density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Caesium chloride is used in the preparation of electrically conducting glasses.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="056" type="4">
	<an>56</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Barium</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Barium carbonate</name>
			<formula>BaCO<sub>3</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>513-77-9</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp>1828 K</mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Also known as witherite, it is used for the preparation of rat poison, in the manufacture of glass and porcelain, and formerly for refining sugar.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Barium chloride</name>
			<formula>BaCl<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>10361-37-2</cas>
			<density>3.856</density>
			<mp>1235 K</mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<classes>
				<class>HT</class>
			</classes>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is used in the manufacture of pigments and is used in fireworks to give a bright green colour.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Barium ferrite</name>
			<formula>BaFe</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is used in magnetic stripe cards. Barium ferrite is a natural crystal that does not absorb moisture, does not corrode, and does not undergo chemical change. Unlike magnetic particles (MP), BaFe does not have to be surface treated, does not have to be chemically stabilized, nor does it have to be maintained in a tightly controlled environment.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Barium nitrate</name>
			<formula>Ba(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>710022-31-8</cas>
			<density>3.24</density>
			<mp>863 K</mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<classes>
				<class>I</class>
				<class>T</class>				
			</classes>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>A component of Baratol (the others being TNT and a binder). When mixed with <elink ref="13">aluminium</elink> powder it forms a high explosive. It is mixed with Thermite to form Thermate-TH3, used in military thermite grenades.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>	
		<compound>
			<name>Barium titanate</name>
			<formula>BaTiO<sub>3</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>12047-27-7]</cas>
			<density>6.02</density>
			<mp>1898 K</mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Barium titanate is used as a dielectric material for ceramic capacitors, and as a piezoelectric material for microphones and other transducers. As a piezoelectric material, it was largely replaced by lead zirconate titanate, also known as PZT.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Polycrystalline barium titanate displays positive temperature coefficient, making it an useful material for thermistors and self-regulating electric heating systems.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Han purple</name>
			<formula>BaCuSi<sub>2</sub>O<sub>6</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>A pigment that has been used in China for over 2,000 years. The terracotta warriors in Xian were dyed with it. Chinese alchemists first synthesized Han Purple from barium <elink ref="29">copper</elink> silicates. It was used in large imperial projects and pottery.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Yttrium barium copper oxide</name>
			<formula>YBa<sub>2</sub>Cu<sub>3</sub>O<sub>7-x</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>107539-20-8</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>YBCO was the first material to become superconducting above 77 K (the boiling point of <elink ref="7">nitrogen</elink>). All materials developed before YBCO became superconducting only at temperatures near the boiling points of liquid <elink ref="2">helium</elink> or liquid <elink ref="1">hydrogen</elink> (20.1 K). The significance of the discovery of YBCO is the break through in the refrigerant used to cool the material to below the critical temperature.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="057" type="9">
	<an>57</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Lanthanum</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Lanthanum carbonate</name>
			<formula></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is a treatment of hyperphosphatemia, primarily in patients with chronic renal failure. It is taken with meals and binds to dietary phosphate, preventing phosphate from being taken-up by the gut.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="058" type="9">
	<an>58</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Cerium</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Ammonium cerium(IV) nitrate</name>
			<formula>(NH<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>Ce(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>6</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>16774-21-3</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>An important component of Chrome etchant, a material that is used in the production of liquid crystal displays (LCDs).</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Cerium(IV) oxide</name>
			<formula>CeO<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>1306-38-3</cas>
			<density>7.65</density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is used in ceramics, to polish glass, and to sensitize photosensitive glass. It is also used in the walls of self-cleaning ovens.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="059" type="9">
	<an>59</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Praseodymium</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Praseodymium(III) chloride</name>
			<formula>PrCl<sub>3</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>PrCl<sub>3</sub> has been used to increase the activity of Pr6O11 catalysts, which can be used for the oxidation of methane to ethene. This process is becoming an important route to ethene for the manufacture of polyethylene (a common plastic)</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="060" type="9">
	<an>60</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Neodymium</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Neodymium magnet</name>
			<formula>Nd<sub>2</sub>Fe<sub>14</sub>B</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>A powerful magnet, they have replaced marginally weaker and significantly more heat-resistant samarium-cobalt magnets in most applications, due mainly to their lower cost. These magnets are very strong in comparison to their mass, but are also mechanically fragile and the most powerful grades lose their magnetism at temperatures above 80 degrees Celsius.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Used for stabilization and angular head motors in computer hard drives, neodymium magnets are also popular with hobbyists, and a small magnet can have amazing properties - it exhibits magnetic braking when moved near a non-magnetic metal due to induced eddy currents.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Neodymium magnets are used for the transducers in the earphones included with Apple's popular iPod music player, as well as in numerous other high-fidelity headphones or buds.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="061" type="9">
	<an>61</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Promethium</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Promethium(III) oxide</name>
			<formula>Pm<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is the most common form of promethium.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="062" type="9">
	<an>62</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Samarium</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Samarium-153-ethylene diamine tetramethylene phosphonate</name>
			<formula></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Used to treat pain when cancer has spread to the bone. Samarium-153 is injected into a vein and distributes throughout the body. Samarium-153 EDTMP homes in on areas where cancer has invaded the bone. Once there, the radioisotope emits beta particles (electrons) which kill the nearby cancer cells. Pain begins to improve in the first week for most people and the effects can last several months. It is commonly used in lung cancer, prostate cancer, breast cancer, and osteosarcoma. Side effects result from radiation to the bone marrow and include thrombocytopenia and leukopenia.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Samarium-cobalt magnet</name>
			<formula>SmCo<sub>5</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>This sort of rare-earth magnet is very powerful, however they are also very brittle and prone to cracking and chipping. This material poses a fire hazard if ground when dry, since the grinding dust has a low temperature ignition point.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="063" type="9">
	<an>63</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Europium</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Europium(III) chloride</name>
			<formula>EuCl<sub>3</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Europium(III) chloride can be used for the preparation of europium(II) chloride by reduction in a gold boat using <elink ref="1">hydrogen</elink> gas while heating slowly to 700&degree;C. The anhydrous chloride may also be used to prepare organometallic compounds of europium, such as bis(pentamethylcyclopentadienyl)europium(II) complexes. Europium(III) chloride can be used as a starting point for the preparation of other europium salts.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="064" type="9">
	<an>64</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Gallium</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Copper indium gallium selenide (CIGS)</name>
			<formula>Cu(Ga,In)Se<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<densityl></densityl>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>					
			<notes>
				<ptxt>CIGS is a new semiconductor used mainly in photovoltaic cells (CIGS cells).</ptxt>
				<ptxt>CIGS solar cells are not as efficient as crystalline silicon solar cells, but they are expected to be substantially cheaper. CIGS can be printed directly onto molybdenum coated glass sheets. Solar cells made from crystalline silicon are made of slices of solid silicon and require therefore more expensive semiconductor material.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Gallium Gadolinium Garnet</name>
			<formula>Gd<sub>3</sub>Ga<sub>5</sub>O<sub>12</sub>)</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density>7.08</density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>A material with good mechanical, thermal, and optical properties. It is typically colourless. It is used in fabrication of various optical components and as substrate material for magneto-optical films. It also finds use in jewellery as a <elink ref="6">diamond</elink> simulant.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="065" type="9">
	<an>65</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Terbium</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Terfenol-D</name>
			<formula>Tb<sub>0.3</sub>Dy<sub>0.7</sub>Fe<sub>1.9</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>The alloy has an extremely high magnetostriction; it expands and contracts in magnetic fields. It sees application in magnetomechanical sensors, actuators, and acoustic and ultrasonic transducers or in naval sonar systems.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Developed in the 1950's at the Naval Ordnance Laboratory in America. It is named after terbium, <elink ref="26">iron</elink> (Fe), Naval Ordnance Laboratory (NOL), and the D comes from <elink ref="66">dysprosium</elink>.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="066" type="9">
	<an>66</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Dysprosium</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Dysprosium Oxide</name>
			<formula>Dy<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub></formula>
			<mass>373</mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>A white, slightly <glink ref="hygroscopic">hygroscopic</glink> powder having specialized uses in ceramics, glass, phosphors, lasers and dysprosium metal halide lamps.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Holmium(III) oxide (Ho<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>) and Dysprosium(III) oxide (Dy<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>) are the most powerfully <glink ref="magord">paramagnetic</glink> substances known.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Terfenol-D</name>
			<formula>Tb<sub>0.3</sub>Dy<sub>0.7</sub>Fe<sub>1.9</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>The alloy has an extremely high magnetostriction; it expands and contracts in magnetic fields. It sees application in magnetomechanical sensors, actuators, and acoustic and ultrasonic transducers or in naval sonar systems.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Developed in the 1950's at the Naval Ordnance Laboratory in America. It is named after terbium, <elink ref="26">iron</elink> (Fe), Naval Ordnance Laboratory (NOL), and the D comes from <elink ref="66">dysprosium</elink>.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="067" type="9">
	<an>67</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Holmium</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Holmium(III) oxide</name>
			<formula>Ho<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub></formula>
			<mass>377.86</mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>A yellow solid, is a compound of holmium sometimes used in making specialty glasses. It was first isolated in 1878 from an impure sample of erbia by Per Teodor Cleve, who named it holmia after the Latin name for his home town, Stockholm.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Holmium(III) oxide (Ho<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>) and Dysprosium(III) oxide (Dy<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>) are the most powerfully <glink ref="magord">paramagnetic</glink> substances known.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="068" type="9">
	<an>68</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Erbium</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Erbium(III) oxide</name>
			<formula>Er<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>12061-16-4</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>A pink solid, is a compound of erbium sometimes used as a colouring for glasses and a dopant for optical fibres and optical amplifiers. It was partially isolated by <blink ref="cqm">Carl Gustaf Mosander</blink> in 1843, and first obtained in pure form in 1905 by <blink ref="gu">Georges Urbain</blink> and Charles James.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="069" type="9">
	<an>69</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Thulium</name>
	<header>
		<ptxt>None of thulium's compounds are commercially important.</ptxt>
	</header>
</element>

<element media="y" index="070" type="9">
	<an>70</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="y">Ytterbium</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Ytterbium(III) oxide</name>
			<formula>Yb<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>1314-37-0</cas>
			<density>9.17</density>
			<mp>2628 K</mp>
			<bp>4343 K</bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Used as a colourant for glasses and enamels, dopant for garnet crystals in lasers and in the manufacture of optical fibres.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="071" type="9">
	<an>71</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Lutetium</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Lutetium aluminum garnet (LuAG)</name>
			<formula>Al<sub>5</sub>Lu<sub>3</sub>O<sub>12</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>A ceramic material that has been proposed for use as a high refractive index lens material. When doped with cerium it also exhibits scintillation with visible luminescence, making it a candidate for high energy photon detection.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="072" type="2">
	<an>72</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Hafnium</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Hafnium diboride</name>
			<formula>HfB<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Hafnium diboride is an ultra-high temperature ceramic. It has a melting temperature of about 3250 degrees Celsius. It is an unusual ceramic, having relatively high thermal and electrical conductivities. It is a grey, metallic looking material. Hafnium diboride has a hexagonal crystal structure, a molar mass of 200.11 grams per mole, and a density of 10.5 grams per cubic centimeter.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Hafnium diboride is often combined with <elink ref="6">carbon</elink>, <elink ref="5">boron</elink>, <elink ref="14">silicon</elink>, silicon carbide, and/or <elink ref="28">nickel</elink> to improve the consolidation of the hafnium diboride powder (sintering). It is commonly formed into a solid by a process called hot pressing, where the powders are pressed together using both heat and pressure.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>The material has potential for use in hypervelocity reentry vehicles such as ICBM heat shields or aerodynamic leading-edges, due to its strength and thermal properties. Unlike polymer and composite material, HfB<sub>2</sub> can be formed into aerodynamic shapes that will not ablate during reentry.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Hafnium diboride is also investigated as a possible new material for nuclear reactor control rods.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Hafnium(IV) oxide</name>
			<formula>HfO<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is used in optical coatings, and as a high-k dielectric in DRAM capacitors. Hafnium based oxides are currently leading candidates to replace <elink ref="14">silicon</elink> oxide as a gate insulator in field effect transistors.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>		
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="073" type="2">
	<an>73</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Tantalum</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Lithium tantalate</name>
			<formula>LiTaO<sub>3</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>12031-66-2</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp>1923 K</mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>A crystalline solid which possesses unique optical, piezoelectric and pyroelectric properties which make it valuable for infrared motion detectors, terahertz generation and detection, surface acoustic wave applications, cell phones and possibly pyroelectric nuclear fusion.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Tantalum carbide</name>
			<formula>TaC</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>12070-06-3</cas>
			<density>1.39</density>
			<mp>4153 K</mp>
			<bp>5773 K</bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>An extremely hard <glink ref="refractory">refractory</glink> ceramic material, commercially used in tool bits for cutting tools. It is usually processed by sintering. It has the appearance of a brown heavy powder. It is sometimes used as a fine-crystalline additive to tungsten carbide <glink ref="alloy">alloys</glink>. It is an important cermet material.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Tantalum carbide-graphite, a composite material developed in Los Alamos National Laboratory, is one of the hardest materials ever synthesized.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Tantalum pentoxide</name>
			<formula>Ta<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>1314-61-0</cas>
			<density>8.2</density>
			<mp>4153 K</mp>
			<bp>2145 K</bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is used to make capacitors in automotive electronics, mobile phones, and pagers, electronic circuitry; thin-film components; and high-speed tools. Due to its high index of refraction, it has been utilized in the fabrication of the glass of many photographic lenses.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Tantalum nitride</name>
			<formula>TaN</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>12033-62-4</cas>
			<density>13.7</density>
			<mp>3363 K</mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is used to create barrier layers between <elink ref="29">copper</elink> and <elink ref="14">silicon</elink> in the manufacture of integrated circuits, to create thin film surface mount resistors as well as other electronic applications.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="074" type="2">
	<an>74</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Tungsten</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Tungsten carbide</name>
			<formula>WC or W<sub>2</sub>C</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>12070-09-9</cas>
			<density>15.8</density>
			<mp>3143 K</mp>
			<bp>6273 K</bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>The most useful of all tungsten compounds. Its extreme hardness makes it useful in the manufacture of cutting tools, abrasives and bearings, as a cheaper alternative to <elink ref="6">diamond</elink>. Tungsten <elink ref="6">carbide</elink> is also used as a scratch-resistant material for jewellery including watch bands and wedding rings.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="075" type="2">
	<an>75</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Rhenium</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Rhenium diboride</name>
			<formula>ReB<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>A synthetic superhard material of hardness comparable to diamond. The production method of this material does not involve high pressures as with other hard synthetic materials, such as cubic boron nitride, which makes production cheap. The compound is formed from a mixture of rhenium, noted for its resistance to high pressure, and <elink ref="5">boron</elink>, which forms short, strong covalent bonds with rhenium. The resulting material is hard enough to scratch diamond.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="076" type="2">
	<an>76</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Osmium</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Osmiridium</name>
			<formula>IrOs</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>An alloy of <elink ref="76">osmium</elink> and <elink ref="77">iridium</elink>, with traces of other platinum group metals, found naturally or man-made.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Osmiridium is used in making fountain pen nibs, surgical equipment, and other high-wear functions.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="077" type="2">
	<an>77</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Iridium</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Osmiridium</name>
			<formula>IrOs</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>An alloy of <elink ref="76">osmium</elink> and <elink ref="77">iridium</elink>, with traces of other platinum group metals, found naturally or man-made.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Osmiridium is used in making fountain pen nibs, surgical equipment, and other high-wear functions.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="078" type="2">
	<an>78</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Platinum</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Oxaliplatin</name>
			<formula>C<sub>8</sub>H<sub>12</sub>N<sub>2</sub>O<sub>4</sub>Pt</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>63121-00-6</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>A platinum-based chemotherapy drug.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="079" type="2">
	<an>79</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Gold</name>	
	<compounds>
			<compound>
			<name>Auranofin</name>
			<formula>C<sub>20</sub>H<sub>35</sub>AuO<sub>9</sub>PS<sup>+</sup></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>34031-32-8</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>An organogold compound classified by the World Health Organization as an antirheumatic agent.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Aurothioglucose</name>
			<formula>AuSC<sub>6</sub>H<sub>11</sub>O<sub>5</sub></formula>
			<mass>392.181</mass>
			<cas>12192-57-3</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>A derivative of the sugar glucose, it is used to treat rheumatoid arthritis.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Sodium aurothiomalate</name>
			<formula>C<sub>4</sub>H<sub>3</sub>AuNaO<sub>4</sub>S </formula>
			<mass>344.097</mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>an organogold compound used for its antirheumatic effects to treat rheumatoid arthritis. In the United Kingdom only this intramuscular injection drug and the orally taken Auranofin are used medically.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>		
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="080" type="2">
	<an>80</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Mercury</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Mercury(II) fulminate</name>
			<formula>Hg(ONC)<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>628-86-4</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<classes>
				<class>HT</class>
			</classes>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is highly sensitive to friction and shock. It is mainly used in blasting caps.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Mercury(II) sulfate</name>
			<formula>HgSO<sub>4</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>7783-35-9</cas>
			<density>6.47</density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Mercury sulfate is used as a catalyst in the production of acetaldehyde from acetylene and water. Methyl mercury is produced as a side product of this conversion. Mercury-containing pollutants from this reaction are held to have caused Minamata disease in Minamata, Japan.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="081" type="5">
	<an>81</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Thallium</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Thallium(I) oxide</name>
			<formula>Tl<sub>2</sub>O</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is used to make special high refractive index glass. Research is continuing into the use of thallium oxide in high temperature superconductors.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="082" type="5">
	<an>82</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Lead</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Lead azide</name>
			<formula>Pb(N<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>13424-46-9</cas>
			<density>4.71</density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<classes>
				<class>T</class>
				<class>E</class>
			</classes>
			<notes>
				<ptxt><elink ref="82">Lead</elink> azide is a toxic and highly sensitive explosive and is usually handled and stored under water in conductive rubber containers. It will explode after a fall of around 150 mm or in the presence of a static discharge of 7 millijoules. Its detonation velocity is around 5.18 km/s (17,500 ft/s). It is used as a detonator for other, secondary, explosives. In a commercially usable form it is a white powder.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Lead(II) oxide</name>
			<formula>PbO</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<classes>
				<class>T</class>
			</classes>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is used in the manufacture of paints and in glass, as well as in vulcanization. A mixture with glycerine sets to a hard, waterproof cement that has been used to join the flat glass sides and bottoms of aquaria.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Lead(II) nitrate</name>
			<formula>Pb(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>10099-74-8</cas>
			<density>4.6</density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<classes>
				<class>C</class>
				<class>HT</class>				
			</classes>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Lead nitrate is used in the manufacture of matches and special explosives such as <elink ref="82">lead</elink> azide, in mordants for dyeing and printing calico textiles, in the manufacture of <elink ref="82">lead</elink> compounds, as heat stabilizer in nylon and polyesters, as coating of photothermograpic paper, and rodenticides.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Lead(II) selenide</name>
			<formula>PbSe</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>12069-00-0</cas>
			<density>1.5</density>
			<mp>1351 K</mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>A semiconductor material that is used in the manufacture of infrared detectors for thermal imaging.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Lead styphnate</name>
			<formula>C<sub>6</sub>HN<sub>3</sub>O<sub>8</sub>Pb</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>15245-44-0</cas>
			<density>1.5</density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>A toxic explosive used as a component in primer and detonator mixtures for less sensitive explosives, such as nitroglycerine.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Lead(II) sulfide</name>
			<formula>PbS</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>1314-87-0</cas>
			<density>7.7</density>
			<mp>1390 K</mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<classes>
				<class>T</class>
			</classes>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Lead sulfide is one of the oldest and most commonly used <elink ref="82">lead</elink> compounds used as a detection element material in various infra-red sensors.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>		
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="083" type="5">
	<an>83</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Bismuth</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Bismuth strontium calcium copper oxide</name>
			<formula>Bi<sub>2</sub>Sr<sub>2</sub>Ca<sub>n</sub>Cu<sub>n+1</sub>O<sub>2n+6</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>A family of high-temperature superconductors and also the first high-temperature superconductors to be discovered which did not contain a <glink ref="ree">rare earth element</glink>.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Bismuth subsalicylate</name>
			<formula>C<sub>7</sub>H<sub>5</sub>BiO<sub>4</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>14882-18-9</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>The active ingredient in the popular medication Pepto-Bismol that is used to treat nausea, heartburn, indigestion, upset stomach, diarrhea and other temporary discomforts of the stomach and gastrointestinal tract. It displays anti-inflammatory action (due to salicylate) and also acts as an antacid and mild antibiotic.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Bismuth telluride</name>
			<formula>Bi<sub>2</sub>Te<sub>3</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>1304-82-1</cas>
			<density>7.7</density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<classes>
				<class>T</class>
			</classes>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is a semiconductor which is an efficient thermoelectric material for refrigeration or portable power generation.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="084" type="0">
	<an>84</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Polonium</name>
	<header>
		<ptxt>Polonium is a highly radioactive metal and very rare, some compounds are known but their usage is limited due the dangers of working with such a radioactive substance. There are no commercially used compounds.</ptxt>
	</header>
</element>

<element media="y" index="085" type="6">
	<an>85</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Astatine</name>
	<header>
		<ptxt>Astatine is a highly radioactive metal and extremely rare, the rarest element known.</ptxt>
	</header>
</element>

<element media="y" index="086" type="7">
	<an>86</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Radon</name>
	<header>
		<ptxt>Some experiments indicate that <elink ref="9">fluorine</elink> can react with radon and form radon fluoride.</ptxt>
		<ptxt>No useful (with exception to those produced for scientific research) or commercial radon compounds exist.</ptxt>
	</header>
</element>

<element media="y" index="087" type="1">
	<an>87</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Francium</name>
	<header>
		<ptxt>Francium is a highly radioactive metal and extremely rare, second only to <elink ref="85">astatine</elink>. No useful or commercial fermium compounds exist.</ptxt>
	</header>
</element>

<element media="y" index="088" type="4">
	<an>88</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Radium</name>
	<header>
		<ptxt>Its compounds colour flames crimson carmine (rich red or crimson colour with a shade of purple) and give a characteristic spectrum. Due to its geologically short <glink ref="hl">half life</glink> and intense radioactivity, radium compounds are quite rare, occurring almost exclusively in <elink ref="92">uranium</elink> ores.</ptxt>
	</header>
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Radium bromide</name>
			<formula>RaBr<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is used in separating radium form uranium ore.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
		<compound>
			<name>Radium chloride</name>
			<formula>RaCl<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass>296.94</mass>
			<cas>10025-66-8</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>The first radium compound to be prepared in a pure state and was the basis of Marie Curie's original separation of radium from barium.[1] The first preparation of radium metal was by the electrolysis of a solution of radium chloride using a <elink ref="80">mercury</elink> cathode.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Radium chloride is still used for the initial stages of the separation of radium from <elink ref="56">barium</elink> during the extraction of radium from pitchblende. The large quantities of material involved (tonnes of ore for milligrams of radium) favour this less costly (but less efficient) method over those based on radium bromide or radium chromate (used for the later stages of the separation).</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>	
</element>

<element media="y" index="089" type="10">
	<an>89</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Actinium</name>
	<header>
		<ptxt>Actinium is a highly radioactive metal and extremely rare. No useful or commercial actinium compounds exist.</ptxt>
	</header>
</element>

<element media="y" index="090" type="10">
	<an>90</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Thorium</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Thorium dioxide</name>
			<formula>ThO<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>1314-20-1</cas>
			<density>9.86</density>
			<mp>3493 K</mp>
			<bp>4673 K</bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>Used to control the grain size of <elink ref="74">tungsten</elink> used for electric lamps. Added to glass, it helps create glasses of a high refractive index and with low dispersion. Consequently, they find application in high-quality lenses for cameras and scientific instruments.</ptxt>
				<ptxt>Mantles in portable gas lights. These mantles glow with a dazzling light (unrelated to radioactivity) when heated in a gas flame.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="091" type="10">
	<an>91</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Protactinium</name>
	<header>
		<ptxt>Protactinium is a highly radioactive metal. No useful or commercial protactinium compounds exist.</ptxt>
	</header>
</element>

<element media="y" index="092" type="10">
	<an>92</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="y">Uranium</name>	
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Uranyl acetate</name>
			<formula>(UO<sub>2</sub>(CH<sub>3</sub>COO)<sub>2</sub>.2H<sub>2</sub>O)</formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas>541-09-3</cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<classes>
				<class>HT</class>
			</classes>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is used as a negative stain in <glink ref="electron">electron</glink> microscopy, in fact, most procedures in electron microscopy for biology require the use of uranyl acetate. 1% and 2% uranyl acetate solutions are used as an indicator, and a titrant in stronger concentrations in analytical chemistry, as it forms an insoluble salt with <elink ref="11">sodium</elink>.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="093" type="10">
	<an>93</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Neptunium</name>
	<header>
		<ptxt>Neptunium is a highly radioactive metal. No useful or commercial neptunium compounds exist.</ptxt>
	</header>
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Neptunium-based superconductor</name>
			<formula>NpPd<sub>5</sub>Al<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>The first neptunium-based superconductor, discovered in Japan in 2007.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="094" type="10">
	<an>94</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="y">Plutonium</name>	
	<header>
		<ptxt>Plutonium reacts readily with <elink ref="8">oxygen</elink>, forming PuO and PuO<sup>2</sup>, as well as intermediate oxides. It reacts with the <glink ref="halogens">halogens</glink>, giving rise to compounds such as PuX<sub>3</sub> where X can be F, Cl, Br or I; PuF<sub>4</sub> and PuF<sub>6</sub> are also seen. The following oxyhalides are observed: PuOCl, PuOBr and PuOI. It will react with <elink ref="6">carbon</elink> to form PuC, <elink ref="7">nitrogen</elink> to form PuN and <elink ref="14">silicon</elink> to form PuSi<sub>2</sub>.</ptxt>
		<ptxt>Plutonium like other actinoids readily forms a dioxide plutonyl core (PuO<sub>2</sub>). In the environment, this plutonyl core readily complexes with carbonate as well as other <elink ref="8">oxygen</elink> moieties (OH<sup>-</sup>, NO<sub>2</sub><sup>-</sup>, NO<sub>3</sub><sup>-</sup>, and SO<sub>4</sub><sup>-2</sup>) to form charged complexes which can be readily mobile with low affinities to soil.</ptxt>
		<ptxt>PuO<sub>2</sub> formed from neutralizing highly acidic nitric acid solutions tends to form polymeric PuO<sub>2</sub> which is resistant to complexation. Plutonium also readily shifts valences between the +3, +4, +5 and +6 states. It is common for some fraction of plutonium in solution to exist in all of these states in equilibrium.</ptxt>
	</header>
</element>

<element media="y" index="095" type="10">
	<an>95</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Americium</name>
	<compounds>
		<compound>
			<name>Americium dioxide</name>
			<formula>AmO<sub>2</sub></formula>
			<mass></mass>
			<cas></cas>
			<density></density>
			<mp></mp>
			<bp></bp>
			<notes>
				<ptxt>It is used as a source of alpha particles, particularly in ionisation-type smoke detectors.</ptxt>
			</notes>
		</compound>
	</compounds>
</element>

<element media="y" index="096" type="10">
	<an>96</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Curium</name>
	<header>
		<ptxt>Curium is a highly radioactive metal. No useful or commercial curium compounds exist.</ptxt>
	</header>
</element>

<element media="n" index="097" type="10">
	<an>97</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Berkelium</name>
	<header>
		<ptxt>Berkelium is a highly radioactive metal. No useful or commercial berkelium compounds exist.</ptxt>
	</header>
</element>

<element media="n" index="098" type="10">
	<an>98</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Californium</name>
	<header>
		<ptxt>Californium is a highly radioactive metal. No useful or commercial californium compounds exist.</ptxt>
	</header>
</element>

<element media="n" index="099" type="10">
	<an>99</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Einsteinium</name>
	<header>
		<ptxt>Einsteinium is a highly radioactive metal. No useful or commercial einsteinium compounds exist.</ptxt>
	</header>
</element>

<element media="n" index="100" type="10">
	<an>100</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Fermium</name>
	<header>
		<ptxt>Fermium is a synthetic and highly unstable element. No useful or commercial fermium compounds exist.</ptxt>
	</header>
</element>

<element media="n" index="101" type="10">
	<an>101</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Mendelevium</name>
	<header>
		<ptxt>Mendelevium is a synthetic and highly unstable element. No useful or commercial mendelevium compounds exist.</ptxt>
	</header>
</element>

<element media="n" index="102" type="10">
	<an>102</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Nobelium</name>
	<header>
		<ptxt>Nobelium is a synthetic and highly unstable element. No useful or commercial nobelium compounds exist.</ptxt>
	</header>
</element>

<element media="y" index="103" type="10">
	<an>103</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Lawrencium</name>
	<header>
		<ptxt>Lawrencium is a synthetic and highly unstable element. No useful or commercial lawrencium compounds exist.</ptxt>
	</header>
</element>

<element media="n" index="104" type="8">
	<an>104</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Rutherfordium</name>
	<header>
		<ptxt>Rutherfordium is a synthetic and highly unstable element. No useful or commercial rutherfordium compounds exist.</ptxt>
	</header>
</element>

<element media="n" index="105" type="8">
	<an>105</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Dubnium</name>
	<header>
		<ptxt>Dubnium is a synthetic and highly unstable element. No useful or commercial dubnium compounds exist.</ptxt>
	</header>
</element>

<element media="n" index="106" type="8">
	<an>106</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Darmstadtium</name>
	<header>
		<ptxt>Seaborgium is a synthetic and highly unstable element. No useful or commercial seaborgium compounds exist.</ptxt>
	</header>
</element>

<element media="y" index="107" type="8">
	<an>107</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Bohrium</name>
	<header>
		<ptxt>Bohrium is a synthetic and highly unstable element. No useful or commercial bohrium compounds exist.</ptxt>
	</header>
</element>

<element media="n" index="108" type="8">
	<an>108</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Hassium</name>
	<header>
		<ptxt>Hassium is a synthetic and highly unstable element. No useful or commercial darmstadtium compounds exist.</ptxt>
	</header>
</element>

<element media="n" index="109" type="8">
	<an>109</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Meitnerium</name>
	<header>
		<ptxt>Meitnerium is a synthetic and highly unstable element. No useful or commercial meitnerium compounds exist.</ptxt>
	</header>
</element>

<element media="n" index="110" type="8">
	<an>110</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Darmstadtium</name>
	<header>
		<ptxt>Darmstadtium is a synthetic and highly unstable element. No useful or commercial darmstadtium compounds exist.</ptxt>
	</header>
</element>

<element media="n" index="111" type="8">
	<an>111</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Roentgenium</name>
	<header>
		<ptxt>Roentgenium is a synthetic and highly unstable element. No useful or commercial roentgenium compounds exist.</ptxt>
	</header>
</element>

<element media="n" index="112" type="8">
	<an>112</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Copernicium</name>
	<header>
		<ptxt>Copernicium is a synthetic and highly unstable element. No useful or commercial copernicium compounds exist.</ptxt>
	</header>
</element>

<element media="n" index="113" type="8">
	<an>113</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Nihonium</name>
	<header>
		<ptxt>Nihonium is a synthetic and highly unstable element. No useful or commercial nihonium compounds exist.</ptxt>
	</header>
</element>

<element media="n" index="114" type="8">
	<an>114</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Flerovium</name>
	<header>
		<ptxt>Flerovium is a synthetic and highly unstable element. No useful or commercial Flerovium compounds exist.</ptxt>
	</header>
</element>

<element media="n" index="115" type="8">
	<an>115</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Moscovium</name>
	<header>
		<ptxt>Moscovium is a synthetic and highly unstable element. No useful or commercial moscovium compounds exist.</ptxt>
	</header>
</element>

<element media="n" index="116" type="8">
	<an>116</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Livermorium</name>
	<header>
		<ptxt>Livermorium is a synthetic and highly unstable element. No useful or commercial Livermorium compounds exist.</ptxt>
	</header>
</element>

<element media="n" index="117" type="8">
	<an>117</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Tennessine</name>
	<header>
		<ptxt>Tennessine is a synthetic and highly unstable element. No useful or commercial tennessine compounds exist.</ptxt>
	</header>
</element>

<element media="n" index="118" type="8">
	<an>118</an>
	<name isotope="y" allotrope="n">Oganesson</name>
	<header>
		<ptxt>Oganesson is a synthetic and highly unstable element. No useful or commercial oganesson compounds exist.</ptxt>
	</header>
</element>

</compoundlist>